<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Toleration disapprov'd and condemn'd by the authority and convincing reasons of I. that wise and learned man King James and his Privvy Council anno reg. 2do, II. the honourable Commons assembled in this present Parliament faithfully collected by a very moderate hand and humbly presented to the serious consideration of all dissenting parties.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26079</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A4047</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25895</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09279681</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09279681</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42597</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26079)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42597)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1299:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Toleration disapprov'd and condemn'd by the authority and convincing reasons of I. that wise and learned man King James and his Privvy Council anno reg. 2do, II. the honourable Commons assembled in this present Parliament faithfully collected by a very moderate hand and humbly presented to the serious consideration of all dissenting parties.</title>
                  <author>Assheton, William, 1641-1711.</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>86, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Oxland Sen. and are to be sold by John Williams,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to William Assheton by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Toleration.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42597:1"/>
            <p>TOLERATION Diſapprov'd and Condemn'd BY THE <hi>Authority and convincing Reaſons</hi> OF
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>That Wiſe and Learned</hi> King James <hi>and his Privy-Council.</hi> Anno Reg. 2<hi rend="sup">do</hi>.</item>
                  <item>II. <hi>The Honourable Commons Aſſembled in this preſent Parliament in their Votes,</hi> &amp;c. Feb. 25. 1662.</item>
                  <item>III. <hi>The Presbyterian Miniſters in the City of</hi> London <hi>met at</hi> Sion-Colledge, Decemb. 18. 1645.</item>
                  <item>IV. <hi>Twenty eminent Divines (moſt (if not all) of them Members of the late</hi> Aſſembly) <hi>in their Sermons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the two Houſes of Parliament on Solemn Occaſions.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> Faithfully Collected <hi>By a very Moderate Hand, and humbly Preſented to the Serious Conſideration of all Diſſenting PARTIES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Oxlad</hi> Sen. and are to be Sold by <hi>John Williams</hi> in <hi>Croſs-Keys</hi> Court in <hi>Little-Brittain,</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_authorities_cited">
            <pb facs="tcp:42597:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Names of thoſe eminent Divines, whoſe Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies are recited, are as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Cornelius Burgeſſe</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>John Ward</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>William Good</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Tho. Thorowgood</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Humph. Hardwick</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Arthur Salwey</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>William Reyner</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas Caſe</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>John Lightfoot</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas Watſon</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>George Hughes</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Edmund Calamy</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas Horton</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Lazarus Seaman</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Mathew Newcomen</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Richard Vines</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Simeon Aſh</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>James Cranford</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas Edwards.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42597:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TOLERATION Diſapprov'd and Condemned, &amp;c. Humbly Preſented to the ſerious Conſideration of all Diſſenting Parties.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Lord Jeſus (who knows all our Hearts, and before whoſe great Tribunal both you and I muſt one day appear) is my witneſs, that the chief deſigne of my preſent Undertaking is the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Welfare</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and the eternal <hi>Salvation</hi> of pretious and immortal <hi>Souls; I</hi> do therefore much hope (though we are all naturally impatient of oppoſition) that you will favourably <hi>receive,</hi> and ſeriouſly <hi>conſider</hi> theſe <hi>plain</hi> (yet well-meaning) <hi>lines;</hi> which have no other <hi>patronage,</hi> then the <hi>charity</hi> of the <hi>Author,</hi> and the <hi>candor</hi> and piety of thoſe <hi>perſons</hi> to whom they are <hi>directed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ſolemnity</hi> of this <hi>Preface</hi> as it may raiſe your expectations, ſo it may poſſibly invite your cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42597:3"/> to inquire, <hi>who</hi> or what manner of perſon I am, that have taken the confidence of ſo important an Addreſs.</p>
            <p>And though the knowledge of my name would ſignifie little, (I being not ſo conſiderable as that it ſhould add any weight to my performance) yet that I may in ſome ſort gratifie ſuch oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Readers</hi> (as I hope to find you) I ſhall far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther acquaint you, that though I am not a perſon very ambitious to be known) yet upon occaſion, I ſhall either publickly <hi>own</hi> and <hi>vindica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> or (if duly convinc'd) as <hi>publickly</hi> recant my preſent <hi>Opinion:</hi> and (in ſhort) to ſecure <hi>you</hi> and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logize for <hi>my ſelf</hi> (ſince concealed Names are ever ſuſpitious) I do ſolemnly proteſt; that I am no ſcoffer at <hi>Religion,</hi> nor Railer at <hi>true</hi> Piety; that I <hi>love</hi> an honeſt Religious good man (that endeavours to <hi>ſave</hi> his <hi>Soul,</hi> and come to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) under what profeſſion ſoever I find him; that I will pitty and (according to my poor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility) rectifie, but never make ſport with his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and miſtakes; and herein I do readily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to the Learned Ld. <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments touching th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe. p. 165.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Verulam, that to turn Religion into a Comedy or Satyr, to ſearch, and rip up Wounds with a laughing countenance; to intermix
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42597:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> Scripture, and ſcurrility ſometimes in one ſentence, is a thing very far from the devout reverence of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and ſcant beſeeming the honeſt regard of a ſober man, two principal cauſes</hi> (ſaith this honourable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) <hi>have I ever known of Atheiſm; curious Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, &amp; prophane ſcoffing.</hi> And no leſs do I admire (what I hope you will grant I have endeavoured to tranſcribe) that incomparable ſaying of the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious <note n="b" place="margin">The Preface to his Eccl. Pol. Sect. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Hooker, There will come a time, when three words uttered with Charity and Meekneſs, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a far more bleſſed Reward, than three thouſand Volumns written with diſdainful ſharpneſs of Wit.</hi> But, if an irregular <hi>heat</hi> (which I will yet endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſuppreſs) ſhould ſome little diſplay it ſelf (it being very difficult to contend <hi>coldly,</hi> and without Affection, about things which we hold dear and precious) (and certainly the Peace of the Church is eminently ſuch) if <hi>Paſſion,</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi> ſhould obtrude themſelves under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Zeal (which God knows, is no leſs the common than fatal miſtake in the management of our Controverſies) I do then humbly beg of you, that you would ſeriouſly conſider the following Word of the fore-cited <hi>good man,</hi> that, <hi>the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of mens writings muſt not alienate our hearts from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42597:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Truth, if it appear they have the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having now (as far as 'tis judg'd convenient) given you an account of the Author, 'twil in all likelihood be next demanded (ſince this Subject hath been of late ſo fully, &amp; as ſome think unanſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werably diſcuſt) what convincing Reaſons I have to trouble, either my Brethren to read, or my ſelf to write, ſo common, and (whileſt propoſals are on foot) ſo unwelcome a Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Really (my Brethren) did <hi>I</hi> not fear, that ſuch frequent proteſtations might ſeem too affected; or that <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Reality,</hi> might be miſtaken for <hi>Humour</hi> and <hi>Deſigne; I</hi> would once more call the ſearcher of all Hearts to witneſs; that <hi>I</hi> am ſo far from a perſecuting ſpirit (the uſual <hi>Brand</hi> we beſtow upon our Adverſaries) that ſome Months ſince I had ſo favourable an opinion of <hi>Indulgence, Connivence,</hi> or <hi>Toleration,</hi> that I little thought I ſhould <hi>now</hi> appear an obſtructer of ſo much <hi>deſir'd,</hi> and (as I then apprended) ſo bleſſed a work.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> am confident you are very forward to know the Reaſon of ſo ſudden, and unexpected a change; tis therefore (omitting all farther prefacing) in ſhort thus:</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:42597:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Being deſirous to inform my ſelf in the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>extent</hi> of <hi>Toleration,</hi> which <hi>I</hi> obſerved (in ſuch variety of <hi>Methods,</hi> by ſuch different <hi>Parties</hi>) ſo zealouſly promoted, (and that under no leſs <hi>titles</hi> than <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> the great <hi>intereſt</hi> of all <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> and particularly of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) in order to a more full ſatisfaction (not omitting my hearty <hi>Prayers</hi> to the <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>Lights,</hi> from <hi>whom</hi> cometh every <hi>good</hi> and <hi>perfect</hi> gift, and who hath promiſed to give <hi>Wiſdome, Counſel,</hi> and <hi>direction</hi> to him that <hi>asketh) I</hi> procur'd, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed ſome of the moſt conſiderable <hi>Tracts</hi> and <hi>Pamphlets (pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi>) that have handled this Subject; and I muſt <hi>ingeniouſly</hi> confeſs (though I was not perfectly convinc'd, yet) I did at firſt very much favour (whom I do <hi>yet</hi> no leſs <hi>pitty</hi>) the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting <hi>Party;</hi> and really it ſeem'd ſo plauſible (ſince every man muſt anſwer for his <hi>own</hi> works) that every man ſhould have the <hi>Liberty</hi> of his <hi>own</hi> opinion; and the name of <hi>Conſcience</hi> is ſo <hi>ſacred;</hi> that <hi>I</hi> durſt not but make a <hi>pauſe,</hi> before <hi>I</hi> had paſſed a <hi>judgement</hi> upon ſuch honeſt pretences. And (to make you my Confeſſors) <hi>I</hi> was not little affected with ſome <hi>reſentments</hi> of a late in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Writer, his words are theſe:</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:42597:5"/>
            <p>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ. for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of King &amp; King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. Pag 10.</note> 
               <hi>There are a company of people about us in the Country of Different peſwaſions, who meet ſometimes many hundreds together, that our Juſtices have been in perplexity what to do: The moſt of them (for ought I perceive) are certainly inoffenſive perſons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and they have really no more againſt them, than Pliny a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Chriſtians of old, when he ſent to</hi> Trajan <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them; that is, only that they meet, and Preach, and Pray together, and if that excellent</hi> Prince <hi>was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd after this report he gave him of them in his Epistle, to have thoſe good men ſought out any more unto puniſhment, I cannot but favour their inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are averſe from the like inquiſitions. I profeſs to God it is ſuch an ungentleman-like thing (me thinks) to trouble ones Neighbours, that I ſhould be glad to rid modeſt men of that work. It were better all theſe Acts ſuffered at once a due and Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulation, than we ſhould be still put upon this unto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward dragging innocent Folk's thus to Priſon, for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing in earnest, but endeavouring to ſave their Souls; in the name of God take you your Pſalter, and let them ſay their Prayers as they will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, together with ſome other Reflections drawn from the great Love of Chriſt to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:42597:5"/> (which therefore by way of <hi>gratitude</hi> we are to <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge</hi> by ſuitable <hi>Acts</hi> of Love, pitty, and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence</hi> to our poor Brethren) did very much <hi>move</hi> me: the words of my Author are theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is a perſon I hope you would do a kindneſs for</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. 72<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>with all your heart, and you have Reaſon, it is for your dear Lord that bought you, and there is nothing in the world you can do I am perſwaded, that he will take ſo kindly from you at this time, as to be pittiful to his Servants, who are diſtreſſed about your Acts in point of Conſcience, and who the more deſpiſed they are and the like unto their Lord, the fitter Subjects they are for your Compaſſion:</hi> And a little after—<hi>If you had no need of Mercy from God, it were tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then for you to be extream towards others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope this can did confeſsion of my weakneſs (if yet it be a weakneſs to acknowledge my Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours) ſhall not ſo far prejudice my Reader, as to hinder his acceptance of my following Reaſons, if it appear that they are really ſuch (<hi>i. e.) rational</hi> and convincing, to give you therefore my Thoughts, in order to my firſt reflection, was this:</p>
            <p>That though this <hi>Toleration</hi> whileſt conſidered in the <hi>Notion,</hi> and as it were in the <hi>Idea,</hi> do carry
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42597:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> with it a great deal of outward glory and luſtre, filling the Hearts of Men with Expectations of much Happineſs to enſue (and no wonder if it be <hi>therefore</hi> entertained with general Applauſe, eſpecially of the Vulgar ſort:) yet when we come <hi>ad practicandum,</hi> to conſider how this notion may beſt be made <hi>practical,</hi> and put in <hi>Execution,</hi> we ſhall then meet with ſuch impediments, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences as ſhall render the performances (to ſay no worſe) very far ſhort of promiſe, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation. And for my own part (ſubmitting ſtill to better Judgements) I do find it ſo <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>npracticable,</hi> that however it is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended (and that very highly) by others, yet in <hi>my</hi> apprehenſion (and indeed the proceſs of the <hi>World</hi> ſheweth no leſſe) <hi>'tis only a Thing for weaker Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to talk on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For (to remind you <hi>onely</hi> of what others have more fully diſcuſs'd) if a <hi>Toleration</hi> muſt be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then either <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlimited</hi> (ſuch as may comprehend even the Papiſts themſelves) or elſe Particular, (<hi>i. e.</hi>) limited to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome peculiar Perſons or Parties.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt, 'tis ſo perfectly wild and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant that (in the judgement of all ſober <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi>)
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42597:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Proteſtants</hi>) it rather deſerves an exploſive ſcorn then a ſerious confutation.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond, <hi>viz.</hi> a particular and <hi>limited,</hi> unleſſe (which ſeemes the likelieſt way to bring the work to ſome <hi>Iſſue</hi>) the Diſſenting parties (who are many, and of different <hi>perſwaſions</hi>) would clearly and diſtinctly acquaint the World (in ſome publick <hi>Writing</hi> Unanimouſly own'd) who they are that ſhall be indulg'd, and upon <hi>what</hi> conditions, we are yet never the nearer.</p>
            <p>They give us indeed (by way of Reſolution) ſome general expreſſions: but theſe then are of ſo <hi>doubtful, (I</hi> had almoſt ſaid impoſsible) inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation; that <hi>I</hi> appeal to any rational man (all prejudice and intereſt lay'd aſide) whether ſuch uncertainties can be <hi>laid</hi> as a ſufficient <hi>Foundation,</hi> on which to <hi>raiſe</hi> ſo conſiderable a <hi>ſtructure</hi> as the <hi>peace</hi> of the Church, and <hi>proſperity</hi> of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>For whilſt they tell us of <hi>Reformed Religion to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſc. of Relig. Title pag</note> 
               <hi>be ſetled in its due Latitude,</hi> and yet never ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint us what we are to underſtand by this <hi>due Latitude,</hi> what is the full extent, and meaning of the <hi>Word:</hi> whileſt they <hi>propoſe, that the Parties</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſc. of Rel. Par. 1 pag. 18</note> 
               <hi>comprehended in their establiſhment ſhall be of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42597:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> in the publick Intereſt, and of Principles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grous to ſuch ſtated Order in the Church, as the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the Common-wealth requires:</hi> and yet never inform us what theſe <hi>important Intereſts,</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grous Principles</hi> are; what other is it, but to trifle us with <hi>Ambiguities</hi> and amuſements? to trouble both themſelves and others, in thus fiercely contending for a <hi>Toleration</hi> in no body know's What, and to be granted to no body know's Whom.</p>
            <p>I have given you a reflection, which if duely improved by ſome happier Pen, might poſſibly, appear of more difficult reſolution, than your preſent <hi>Sentiments</hi> (occaſion'd by the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of its delivery) may invite you to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend.</p>
            <p>However, I am ſure (as to me) it hath been of ſufficient moment, to <hi>reviſe</hi> my former Thoughts; and to ſhew leſſe <hi>kindneſs</hi> to your preſent Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, towards which I have been (very lately) more warmly affected.</p>
            <p>But (to come cloſer to my intendment) that which did more <hi>fully</hi> (and if I miſtake not, unanſwerably) convince me, was the peruſal of ſeveral Sermons preached by ſome of our
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42597:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> late eminent Divines) before the two Houſes of Parliament) on ſolemn occaſions, for I muſt not omit to tell you; that having heard thoſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes much commended (as being delivered by ſuch famous Preachers; before ſuch as were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted ſo wiſe and judicious Auditors as the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> and therefore without doubt did contain ſomewhat extraordinary) I procured a good number of them (about an hundred) and as my other occaſions would permit, not without much expectation ſet my ſelf to the reading of them.</p>
            <p>And indeed (that I may be faithful to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of thoſe perſons) I muſt acknowledge both to you and the world, <hi>I</hi> received no bad return of my Labours, for <hi>I</hi> found (which is cheifly to my preſent purpoſe to obſerve) This point of <hi>Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> ſo excellently, and fully diſcuſſed, though <hi>obi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> onely and as it were <hi>by</hi> the <hi>by,</hi> that no Tract <hi>ex inſtituto</hi> (and there are ſome very ingenious) could ever aford me the like ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>Now that this may not be <hi>gratis and precario dictum, I</hi> ſhall very <hi>Faithfully</hi> lay down their <hi>own Reaſons</hi> in their <hi>own Words,</hi> and then leave it to <hi>you</hi> and all men to conſider, Whether it be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42597:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> not (morally at leaſt) impoſsible that ſo many <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently learned,</hi> and eminent Divines ſhould ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, (and that with ſuch vehemency of Zeal) oppoſe the very <hi>Name</hi> of Toleration (and which is yet more obſervable, that thoſe very <hi>Sermons</hi> in which theſe invectives are contained, ſhould not only receive the <hi>Thanks</hi> of the Two Houſes, but by their eſpecial order, be likewiſe made <hi>Publick</hi>) were there not ſome ſecret <hi>Danger in</hi> the <hi>Thing,</hi> which either the <hi>Intereſt,</hi> or <hi>Security</hi> of the preſent <hi>Age,</hi> will not <hi>now</hi> ſuffer us to <hi>Apprehend.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>I ſpeak as unto Wiſe men, Judge ye what I ſay.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_authorities_cited">
            <pb facs="tcp:42597:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42597:9"/>
            <list>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Cornelius Burgeſſe</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>John Ward</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>William Good</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Tho. Thorowgood</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Humph. Hardwick</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Arthur Salwey</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>William Reyner</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas Caſe</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>John Lightfoot</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas Watſon</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>George Hughes</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Edmund Calamy</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas Horton</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Lazarus Seaman</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Mathew Newcomen</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Richard Vines</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Simeon Aſh</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>James Cranford</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr. Thomas Edwards.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <div type="authorities">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:42597:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>The Teſtimonies of the fore-mentioned <hi>Divines againſt Toleration.</hi>
               </head>
               <q>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr. Corn. Burgeſſe Serm. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the houſe of Commons</hi> Novem. 5. 1641. <hi>p.</hi> 60. London, <hi>printed for C. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redith at the Crane in</hi> S. Pauls <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. 1641.</hi>
                  </note>GIve me leave, I beſeech you, to ſpeak freely to you; I will do it humbly too.</q>
               <q>At your firſt ſitting down, you expreſſed many brave and noble Reſolutions, of giving Gods buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the precedency of all other your Affairs: and your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings promiſed much. Howbeit, I know not how it comes to paſs, but ſo it is, that Gods work lies yet undone. Matters of Religion lie a bleeding; all Government and Diſcipline of the Church is laid in her Grave, and all putredinous Vermine of bold Schiſmaticks and Frantick Sectaries glory in her Actes, making her fall their own riſing to mount our Pulpits, to offer ſtrange fire, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the graveſt, ableſt, and moſt eminent Miniſters in the Kingdome; (if not out of their Pulpits yet) out of the Hearts of their People, as a company of weak men, <hi>Formaliſts, Time-ſervers,</hi> no Miniſters of Chriſt, but <hi>Limbs of Antichriſt;</hi> having no calling except from the Devil; and to forſake our Aſſemblies as Babyloniſh and <hi>Antichriſtian;</hi> ſo as in ſhort time they will not leave us the face of a Church. And yet <hi>No Courſe is taken to ſuppreſs their fury and to reduce them to Order,</hi> which (as things now ſtand) will never be, till you put your hands to the Cure. I beſeech you therefore, in the<note place="margin">P. 63.</note> Name of that great God, whom you ſerve, and who hath hitherto bleſt you, and for the Peace and Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of this Church and Kingdome, to reſume and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42597:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> purſue your firſt thoughts of ſetting up God and his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, as becomes you in a regular way—that our Church and the Government thereof may be no longer laid waſte, and expoſed to Confuſion, under the plauſible<note place="margin">P. 64.</note> pretence of <hi>Not forcing mens Conſciences.</hi> To put all men into a courſe of <hi>Order</hi> and Uniformity, in Gods way, is not to force the Conſcience; but to ſet up God in his due place, and to bring all his people into the paths of righteouſneſs and life.</q>
               <q>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Commons at a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faſt</hi> March 30. 1642 p. 35.</note>Be there none of you that fore-ſee the fatal miſchiefes of leaving all men to their liberties in the things of God, and yet want hearts to uſe your Skill and Intereſt, to make haſt to ſetle matters of Religion, leſt you come too late with a Remedy when the Diſeaſe is grown in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable, and the Kingdome grown to that paſs (as the grave Hiſtorian noted of old <hi>Rome</hi>) that it can neither bear the malady, nor endeavour the Cure? Do you not ſee or hear daily of the Diſorders, Sects, Rents, and Schiſms<note place="margin">P. 46.</note> that every where bud forth already, and threaten all Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Unity, and Governments? give the water but a paſſage without ſpeedy making up the Banks, and you Know how ſome whole Seas will break in upon us, and render all irrecoverable and incurable. If one difficulty occurs to day, it will be doubled, yea multiplyed to morrow. There is no <hi>Hydra</hi> ſo fertile of heads, as Errour and Schiſme grown to ſome ſtrength and maturity, it will ask you but a ſhort time of <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nivances</hi> afterwards: there will be no curbing nor ſhaming of it. Nothing is ſo confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as ignorance, impudent as falſhood, and catching as Errours.</q>
               <q>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Commons at a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faſt</hi> April 30 1645. p. 5. <hi>&amp; 52.</hi>
                  </note>Take heed of thoſe ſpirits of Errour, who with fair (ſpeciouſe, pargetted, gloing words ſeek to make
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42597:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> merchandize of you, beguiling unſtable Souls. Beware of thoſe compliances with, and Indulgences to all ſorts of Sects and Schiſms now pleaded for, both by word and writing, as it were a part of Chriſts Legacy, and his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples liberty to be of what Religion they will; to be tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in any opinions never ſo erroneous and pernicious (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til further light:) that it is the Magiſtrates duty to protect them in that liberty; and that the contrary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto is to perſecute Chriſt.</q>
               <q>Hath God inſerted this as one main branch of his Grand Covenant with his People under the Goſpel, I will give them one heart and one way that they may fear me for ever; * that is, that they may all call upon the name of<note place="margin">Jer. 32. 39.</note> the Lord to ſerve him with one conſent? <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3. 9. Did Chriſt aſcend up on high and give gifts unto men, and gave ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, and ſome Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers, for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtery, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt, till we all come, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> into the unity of the Faith; and, is it Perſecution, and Antichriſtianiſme to engage all to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niformity?</hi> Doth <hi>Paul</hi> bid the <hi>Philippians</hi> to beware of the Conciſion? <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 2. Doth he beſeech the <hi>Romans</hi> to mark thoſe which cauſe Diviſions and Offences, contrary to the Doctrine which they had learned, and to<note place="margin">
                     <hi>And yet the Author of Libert. of Conſc.</hi> (p. 32.) <hi>tells us that this Text is little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</hi>
                  </note> avoid them; and that upon this ground, that they who are ſuch, ſerve not the Lord Jeſus, but their own bellies, however by good words and fair ſpeeches they deceive the Hearts of the ſimple? <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 17. Doth he writing to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> wiſh, <hi>I would they were even cut off that trouble you,</hi> Gal. 5. 12. And it is ſuch an hainous offence now, for the Faithful Servants of Chriſt,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42597:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> to adviſe you to the ſame courſe? O Heavens! be aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed at this; and bluſh for the Ignorance of ſome, and Impudence of others, that dare ſo boldly preſs for ſuch a <hi>Toleration</hi> which none but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain deſtructive thoughts of carnal men can look upon without indignation and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</q>
               <q>Beware how you hearken to theſe Empiricks and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens, who ſeek to Charm the World into a deep Sleep, by preſenting their Confidence of a neceſſity of comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with all ſorts of Sectaries, yea of truſting the Sword in their hands, and to defer the ſetling of matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion during the War, for fear of loſing the <hi>Godly</hi> Party (as too many proudly ſtile themſelves, by way of difference from all that are not of their opinions and ways) what is this but to teach God a new Form of Politicks, to proclaim, that it is not always ſafe to hold out the Truth of the Goſpel, and to command all men to embrace it, but much ſafer to halt between two opinions? Belike <hi>Joſiah</hi> went beyond his bounds, when after himſelf had ſworn a ſolemn Covenant to the Lord, he made all <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Benjamin</hi> to ſtand to it, and made all that were preſent in <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſerve the Lord their God. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34. 32, 33. and <hi>Aſia</hi> much more, when he drew all the people into a Covenant, <hi>That whoſoever would not ſeek the Lord God of Iſrael, ſhould be put to Death, Whether ſmall or great, Man or Woman,</hi> 2 Chron. 15. 13. <note n="b" place="margin">The Author of Lib. of Conſ. p. 28. aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures us the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, when he tells us that what was done by the Kings of Iſrael &amp; Judah, cannot be reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly made a rule to Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel.</note> But the amble and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendant Commendations which the Lord gives unto theſe pious Kings, eſpecially in reference to their ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and zeal in reforming and ſetling of Religion in one <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niform</hi> way, may ſufficiently warrant and encourage all Religious Magiſtrates; to take care that all under their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42597:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> Government, ſhould all ſerve the Lord <hi>with one ſhoulder;</hi> this being not a Tyranny over men, but the Priviledge, of the Goſpel. Beware yet, at laſt, of that thought, that <hi>it is not yet time to build the Lords houſe, Judah</hi> paid dear for this, as I have heretofore ſhew'd you at large, on <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 76. 10. and in my former <hi>Sermon</hi> on this Text; and therefore, ſhall ſpare my ſelf and you the pains of inlarging at the preſent. Setle this in your hearts; Gods Truth, the true Worſhip and Diſcipline of Chriſt, ſet up and eſtabliſhed in one Uniform way., never preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced any Nation or State (where it had free paſſage) in the leaſt degree, but hath ever been their ſafety, happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and honour. It is Errour (how much ſoever cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up) not truth, (how much ſoever cryed down and blaſphemed) that makes and foments Rents and Factions. <hi>Honourable and Beloved;</hi> yet another word of Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>John Ward of</hi> Ipſwich <hi>in his Serm. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Commons</hi> March 26. 1645. <hi>p. 49. London printed for</hi> C. Mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith. 1645.</note> to judge for God, and as God judgeth. 1. For God. There are matters of God, as well as matters of the King or Kingdom; the care whereof muſt be upon you as well as upon us; his Church, his Kingdom, his City, his Houſe, his People, his Spouſe, his Children, his Body ye as nurſing Fathers, muſt tender the good and welfare of them, that they may find Harbour, and Protection, enjoy their juſt Priviledges, and Liberties, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Chriſt had made them free: not ſuch Licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as is abus'd for a Cloak of Naughtineſs. Ye muſt ſee to Order and Unity amongſt them, that there be no Rents and Schiſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; ſurely our Saviour that Aſcended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Heaven, and gave gift to men, ſome Apoſtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that wee might all meet in the Unity of the Faith; and hath divers times, and after ſundry manners, given that very thing in Charge to his Miniſters, would not have the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42597:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> Magiſtrate left at large from providing, and endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that ſpeaking or following the truth in love, we may grow up, making increaſe by edifying our ſelves and one another in Love.</q>
               <q>Ye muſt do that, which we are to pray that ye do, <hi>viz.</hi> Take a Courſe that Chriſtians may live in a Peaceable and quiet life in Godlineſs and Honeſty, not in ſtrife and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</q>
               <q>There is—his name, it may not be blaſphemed, diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured. This day, it muſt be ſanctified.</q>
               <q>This Goſpel. Ye have Authority, and it is your duty to provide that it be duly preached: That it be truly taught: not blended, adulterated, made another Goſpel.<note place="margin">P. 50.</note> This worſhip; it muſt not be corrupted by Idolatry, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, <hi>Innovations,</hi> leſt God be worſhipped in vain while they teach for Doctrines the Commandments of men. This Miniſtery; it ought to be purged, planted, lights ſet up in every Bowl of the Candleſtick, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, maintained, and abetted in the work of the Lord.</q>
               <q>Theſe Sacraments; it is your honour as your duty to ſe that they be kept pure in the celebration and miniſtration of them. There is a booker caſe for it. <hi>Numb.</hi> 9. 7. There were certain men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but if this be not full, the Preſidents. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> ch. 15. ch. 30. and ch. 35. will rule the Caſe for the Civil Magiſtrate, and make out this: That where the Doctrine and Diſcip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e of the Church doth not, or cannot prevail, the Magiſtrate muſt interpoſe his Coercive Power for reſtraint and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy.—In a word: God hath many things amongſt us that muſt be protected and maintain'd; and the matters of God have many adverſaries which muſt be watched,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42597:12"/> and ſuppreſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; for ye bear not the ſword in vain<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ye are Gods Miniſters attending continually upon this very thing. Magiſtrates and Miniſters have (as ye ſee) one common ſtyle of Office; that ye in the place, and we in our Function and Order, ſhould mind and promote the things of God; ye by the Sword, and we by the Word; you are Keepers of both Tables, the firſt and great Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">P. 15.</note> as well as the ſecond that is like unto it; both come ſometimes as occaſion is, under your cognizance.</q>
               <q>And ye know what a brand ſticks to this day upon <hi>Gallio</hi> (though an Heathen Magiſtrate) that he cared not for the matters of the Law and Worſhip, (according to the Law) when queſtion was brought; no, though there were Inſurrections and Tumults upon that occaſion: and for <hi>Gamaliels</hi> counſel, <hi>Refrain from theſe men and let them alone: for if this Counſel or this Work, be of men, it will come to nought; but if it be of God, ye cannot over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw it, leſt happily ye be found even to fight againſt God</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>If this be true, the Auth. of the Prop. for King and Kingdom ſhewed more zeal than know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, when ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Counſel of</hi> Gama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liel, <hi>he thus addes. I wiſh to the Lord, the great Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of our ſtate would be content to be no wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer men then</hi> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliel. p. 36. p. 26.</note>. Though it be found within the Bible, yet it is not of like Authority with one of <hi>Solomons</hi> Proverbs or Maxims of Policy: It hath no otherwiſe the approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God for good, then the Deſigne of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> or the crafty Counſel of <hi>Achitophel,</hi> which are alſo recorded in the Scripture: it will not conſiſt with other rules of the Word, and it hath been condemned as unſound, and unſafe by many godly wiſe men; we have more ſure words of Scripture, out of which we draw the Doctrine of the Magiſtrates power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd duty in the matters of God and Religion, then the looſe ſpeech of ſuch a Neutraliſt and time-ſerving Politician as <hi>Gamaliel</hi> was. Go on there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I beſeech you as you began; take us the little Foxes as well as the ravening Wolves; Theſe be they who ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42597:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> themſelves, ſenſual, not having th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Spirit. They Boaſt indeed (much) of the ſpirit, but they manifeſtly do the works of the Fleſh. They plead for liberty, but it is licentiouſneſs. <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> they term it, but it is Liberty of Practice, that every man may do what is good and right in his own eyes: they pretend to nothing but Piety and Godlineſs, and ſeem as if they would be content if they might but have a bare ſubſiſtance in the profeſſion of it. So did the Jeſuits to learning, when they firſt appeared upon the Stage, but when they had once inſinuated themſelves into the good Opinion of Princes and States, how well they anſwered the Expectations; and requited the kindneſs of thoſe who nurſed them up, all the Chriſtian World ſees and feels to their coſt at this day. They ask but <hi>Connivance and Toleration,</hi> but if they once meet in a Confluence, and find themſelves ſtrong enough to run in a ſtream; let but a Damm be Pitcht down to reſtrain or oppoſe their Madneſs, or men fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low not on, to indulge and gratifie their humour, it would ſoon appear, whether or no they rage and ſwell and get over, or bear down afore them all that ſhould ſtand in their way. They did ſeem a while to cry up the <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Parliaments</hi> and of the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate,</hi> and have their perſons in admiration, but meerly for advantage, that ſo they may get above all Eccleſiaſtical Authority; and when they are once up to their height, what they will do with the Ladder, they hope to climb and aſcend by, is not hard to conjecture; they reckon themſelves the Wheat in the Field, and when once they are ripe, they will eaſily be content to have all that threſhed of, by which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived their growth. Ye have heard of the Fable of the Snake and the Country-man that brought it unto the fire,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42597:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> I ſhall not need to apply it, already they begin to remove the old Land-marks and ſtraiten their Bounds, they deny their claim up to an high Water-mark, and make their Banks, and incloſe for themſelves to the very Channel ſide: But whether it be holden fit or ſeaſonable that theſe <hi>Libertines</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e decried; for my part, I cannot yet diſcover by any activeneſs to ſuppreſs them: only ſeeing the evil and fore-ſeeing the miſchief, I have given the warning, that at leaſt I may deliver mine own Soul. I pray God the Remedy be not deferred till it be too late, and ye be driven to play an after-game to an extream hazard and diſadvantage.</q>
               <q>I doubt not but your Souls abhor that bloody Tenet<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Wil. Good, Serm. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Commons,</hi> March 26. 1645. <hi>p. 36. London printed for C.</hi> Mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith. 1645.</note> to the Souls of men, That it is the duty of the Magiſtrate to Tolerate all Religions. You have carried out the Duſt behind the door, and this Opinion will bring all the mire in the ſtreets into the houſe of God again. <hi>Cambyſes</hi> had a luſt to marry his Siſter, and his Counſellors told him, there was no Law whereby to do it: But withall they told him, there was a Law that the Kings of <hi>Perſia</hi> might do what he liſt, and by this he might marry his Siſter. What it is that ſhall be unlawful, if this be lawful, for every man to make a Law and Religion for himſelf?</q>
               <q>Put ſome ſtop by your Authority to the growth of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, that are deſtructive, to the power of Godlineſs, and let not this ſuſpend your Sanction, becauſe ſome that broach them pretend to <hi>Godlineſs;</hi> an enemy, the more like he is to a Friend, the more dangerous.</q>
               <q>The third Uſe of Confutation; it is of the <hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrants,</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:42597:14"/>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Sure this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman is miſtaken, I always thought Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrants and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians had been the ſame.</note> 
                  <hi>Arminians</hi> and <hi>Socinians,</hi> who endeavour from<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Tho. Thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goods Serm. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Commons at a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn faſt</hi> Dec. 25. 1644. <hi>p. 10. his Text,</hi> Phil 4. v. 5. <hi>Let your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration be known unto all men. Lond. Pr. for Chr. Meredith 1645.</hi>
                  </note> my Text, to get countenance for that Babyloniſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ror, the allowance of all opinions, as if becauſe the Apoſtle ſaith, Let your moderation be known unto all men; therefore all Mens Conceits muſt be born with in Religion, and every one ſuffered in what he ſuppoſeth to be Truth: it is a cunning and couſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing Deviſe, that ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>es in with corrupt nature; but becauſe it offers violence to my Text, I cannot be true to it, or you, if ſomewhat be not added by way of Vindication; and it ſhall be in theſe Six Particulars. Firſt, is it probable that our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, who elſwhere, almoſt every where, is ſo zealous for Unity againſt Schiſms, ſhould in any ſort Tolerate them, and ſo voluntarily open a wide Door for diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? In this very Epiſtle he writes for Peace even paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately but with might Power, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 1, 2. If there be any Conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of Love, if any fellowſhip of the ſpirit, if any bowels and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, fulfill ye my joy, that ye be like-minded, having the ſame Love, being of one accord, and of one mind. And in the next Chap. 3. 16.—Let us walk by the ſame Rule, let us mind the ſame thing: Expreſſions different from all licentious Tolerations: The ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle abounds in ſerious Dehortations from Schiſmes and Diſſentions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 12, 16, 17. and as carnal. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 3. and in other places: And he doth very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten exhort with earneſt words and arguments, not only that we be like-minded, <hi>Rom. 15. 6. Phil.</hi> 2. 2. and of one mind, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 12. but of the ſame mind, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 10. joyned, yea joynted together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgment: And is here the leaſt approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that multiplying Doctrine? neither will that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42597:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo long as they all breath Chriſt, tend to the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt; it matters not: but let St. <hi>Paul</hi> anſwer this Objection alſo, is <hi>Chriſt</hi> divided? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 13. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it well, and ſeaſon your conſideration with that of our Maſter Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Mar.</hi> 9. 50. Have ſalt in your ſelves, and have peace one with another: If we were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ty from the corruptions of ſelf-opinion, it would be no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rd matter to embrace unity</q>
               <q>Secondly, ſuch allowance would prove deſtructive to Holineſs both Perſonal and Domeſtical; <hi>Omnis Religio &amp; nulla Religio,</hi> would ſoon be the ſame: Suppoſe the Husband of one opinion, the Wife of another, the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, it may be, of one or two other, and the Servants of as many more; what ſhall the Maſter of the houſe do here? how perform the Family duties? diverſity of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, like ſo many Hatchets interrupting their Prayers, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 7. chopping all Devotion and Piety in pieces: as the Duke of <hi>Wittenberge</hi> was wont to ſay, New Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> introduce new Manners, new Manners bring in new Men, and new Men thruſt out the old; ſo Opinions ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered will devour the old; and the <hi>Toleration</hi> of every Religion will deſtroy all Religion: and in concluſion leave no Religion at all.</q>
               <q>Thirdly, this Liberty is inconſiſtent with civil tranquility; the bleeding condition of our own Nation at preſent, is a living, almoſt a dying witneſs of this: and if that one Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of Popery, ſo tolerated as it was, hath brought in upon us ſo many deſtructions; what will that multiplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion do, but haſten deſolation without recovery; for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part would endeavour to ſupport it ſelf, to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the reſt; <hi>et dum de Religione certatum eſt Regio,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42597:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> dum de caelo terra amiſſa,</hi> as it was ſaid long ſince.</q>
               <q>Fourthly, the late Biſhops of <hi>Ireland</hi> may put this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to ſilence and ſhame; for when not long ſince a <hi>Toleration</hi> of Popery in that Kingdom was propoſed, they ſaid; To give the Papiſts a <hi>Toleration</hi> is a grievous ſin, and will make us acceſſary to all their Abomination, and the perdition alſo of ſeduced Souls.</q>
               <q>Fifthly, this may be currant Doctrine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ongſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> and <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Prop. p. 20. highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends this judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the</hi> wiſe <hi>Emperour</hi> Solyman <hi>and is ſorry that his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary is of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.</hi>
                  </note> the grand Seignior told his M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i; that is, his chief Prieſt, As a Garden is beautified with varity of flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, ſo his Empire would be adorned with diverſities of Religion: let ſuch <hi>Toleration</hi> find allowance in the <hi>Turk's</hi> Paradiſe; it ſhall never, I truſt, be planted in the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of God.</q>
               <q>Sixthly, We have undertaken all in the National Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, the eſtabliſhment of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity;</hi> and how can that ſtand with this <hi>Omniformity</hi> indeed <hi>Nulliformity,</hi> I underſtand not: it was a prodigious thing in the dayes of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> the Prophet, <hi>Jer. 2. 28. According to the Number of thy Cities, are thy Gods, O Judah:</hi> Here would ſoon appear another kind of multiplying and increaſe; but though this Fancy be never ſo plauſible, Divine provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath ſhut it out of our Camp by our Covenant, a<note place="margin">M. <hi>Hump. Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick, Serm. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Commons</hi> June 26. 1644. <hi>p.</hi> 43. London, <hi>printed for C. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redith. 1645.</hi>
                  </note> thing pleaſing to God and profitable to the Kingdoms, by which there is, and through Gods bleſſing may be the moſt famous Blow given to the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and her Baſtard Imps that ever yet was: Now to have this ſtick amongſt us, or laid aſide, whilſt Malignants and Sectaries live in our Boſome, bleſſing, and in ſecret applauding themſelves, that they have neither taken this, nor any of your former proteſtations. This is our caſe and I appeal to wiſer Judgments, whether this may
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42597:15"/> not be the way to Leſſen the Honour and Authority of the High Court of Parliament. Conſider I beſeech you (<hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Arth. Salwey before the Commons,</hi> Octo. 25. 1643 <hi>p.</hi> 19. Lond. <hi>Pr. for C. Meredith 1644.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Chriſtians</hi>) that the Vows of God are upon you, you have abjur'd Neutrality in your late ſolemn Covenant, far be it from any of you to glory in a luke-warm indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency, as if it were a piece of ſingular Policy: you have with your Tongues renounced this Neutrality as deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Follow the Lord in promoting a National Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, you have an admirable Pattern; the zealous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Elijah:</hi> I wiſh from my Soul that a double portion of his Spirit, may be given unto you, that you may act in his Power and Spirit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Elijah</hi> oppos'd Idolatry and Oppreſſion, ſo do ye: down with <hi>Baals Altars,</hi> down with <hi>Baals</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Dedus, Chapters,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Prieſts;</hi> do not (I beſeech you) conſent unto a <hi>Toleration</hi> of <hi>Baals</hi> Worſhip in this Kingdom upon any Politick conſideration whatſoever—Give me leave to be your Humble Remembrancer, the mouths of your Adverſaries are opened againſt you; the hearts of your true Friends are griev'd, that ſo <note n="b" place="margin">Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts.</note> many Delinquents are in Priſon, and yet but very few of them brought to their tryal. Ye cannot preach, nor pray them <note n="c" place="margin">Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and Hereſies.</note> down direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Willi. Reyner before the Commons,</hi> Aug. 28. 1644. <hi>p. 12.</hi>
                  </note> and immediately—well, that which the <hi>Word</hi> cannot do, the <hi>Sword</hi> ſhall; that which the Water cannot waſh out, the Fire will burn out; unto this particular the Apoſtle apply's this very <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai</hi> 26, 7. Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d. <hi>printed for</hi> Sam. Enderby 1644.</note> Text in part, namely concerning the ſhaking of the Heavens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> an Earthquake (as wee have heard) was appointed to ſhake down the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Ordinances; Now if this were neceſſary for the abolition of that Divine Worſhip, which had ſometimes been by Gods own holy Inſtitution, how much more ſhall that which hath been of Humane Invention (yea the very fumes and fogs of the bottomleſs Pit) to Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42597:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> diſpleaſure and diſhonour, be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>bled down with Violence, and Vengeance to Hell, form whence it came.</q>
               <q>There is a word of Exhortation behind, and I beſeech<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Tho. Caſes Sermon before the Commons,</hi> May 26. 1647. <hi>p. 33. Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don print. for Luke Fawne at the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rot in</hi> Pauls <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. 1647.</hi>
                  </note> you ſuffer it.</q>
               <q>Firſt, to you <hi>Honourable and noble Patriots,</hi> who are called to be Reformers and Healers of a poor broken Kingdom. Doth not indeed the puniſhing and ſuppreſſing of ſpiritual Whordoms againſt God, Idolatry, Hereſie, Blaſphemy, and the reſt: doth it not belong unto you, as well as the puniſhing bodily Whordoms, Theft, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>&amp;c.?</hi> doth it indeed belong to you only to look to the Civil peace, and to let Religion, and Truth, and the Worſhip of God ſtand or fall to their own Maſter? fight God, fight Devil, fight Chriſt, fight Antichriſt; catch that catch can; you have nothing to do but to ſtand by and look on<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſay ſo then; ſpeak out, publiſh it in your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations to the World, and let the People of <hi>England</hi> know, that it is the right and liberty, to which the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> are born, that every man hold what he pleaſe, and publiſh, and preach what he holds: that it is the Birth right (as ſome would have it) of the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born people of <hi>England,</hi> Every man to worſhip God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own Conſcience; and to be of what Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion his own Conſcience ſhall dictate: do ſo, and ſee (Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Brethren) how long your Civil peace will ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure you when Religion is deſtroyed; how long it will be ere your Civil peace be turned into Civil War! for no doubt if this once be granted them, but they may in good time come to know alſo (there be them that are inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, even in theſe principles too) that it is their birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right to be freed from the Power of Parliaments, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42597:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> from the power of Kings; <hi>And to take up Arms againſt both, when they ſhall not vote and act according to their humours.</hi> Liberty of Conſcience (falſly ſo called) may in good time, improve it ſelf into liberty of Eſtates, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Houſes, and liberty of Wives, and in a word li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of perdition of Souls and Bodies.</q>
               <q>Right Honourable and worthy Gentlemen: I cannot ſtand to diſpute<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This only would I know of you; Are I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters, and Hereticks, and Blaſphemers, and Seducers, are they evil doers? if ſo, then look to your charge. <hi>Rom. 13. 3. 4. Rulers</hi> muſt be <hi>a Terror to evil Doers,</hi> unleſs ye mean <hi>to bear the Sword in vain<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> And if you will, God will not, and if God take the Sword into his own hand once, (as he ſeems to be a doing of it) he will ſmite to purpoſe; he will execute Vengeance throughly: both upon the evil doers, and upon you that have not been a Terror to them. Oh therefore up and being doing, that ye may deliver the Kingdome out of the hand of the Lord; for it is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God. O let not your patience (I hope it is no more all this while) be interpreted a Connivence, and your Connivence be taken for a Toleration, it may be the Kingdoms ruine, but it will be your ſin.</q>
               <q> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm. before the Com.</hi> Feb. 19. 1645. <hi>p. 25.</hi>
                  </note> Fathers and Brethren, how will ye call this keeping of Covenant with God? Had we a Parliament of Apoſtate <hi>Julians,</hi> of whom it is reported, that at what time he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened the Temples of the Heatheniſh Gods, he ſet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the Chriſtian Churches; call'd home all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians whom he had baniſh't, both Orthodox and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, and gave them (as we call it) Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; but as <hi>Auſtin</hi> more truly phraſeth it, <note n="b" place="margin">Aug. Ep. 166. vid Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian. Marcel. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2. p. 208. 209 Edit. Hen Valeſii. Defence of the Prop. Calls this of Julian a brave and Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke thing. p. 98.</note> 
                  <hi>Libertatem perditionis,</hi> Liberty to deſtroy themſelves; for that was
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42597:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> his Policy and end, namely by libert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of all Religion, to<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eo modo putans Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men poſſe perire de terris,</hi> &amp;c.</note> deſtroy the True, and the Profeſſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> therefore too, Or had we a Parliament of careleſs <hi>Gallio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> we ſhould not wonder: but for a Parliament of Chriſtians, Proteſtants, Profeſſors, the Choiſeſt, the moſt active that could be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out of a Chriſtian Sate, the like not under Heaven; that theſe things ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owdone, and you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>old your peace, and be able to keep your places<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and not to put on Righteouſneſs as a Breſt-plate, and the Garments of Vengeance for your Cloathing, as it is ſaid of God; this makes the Churches abroad to wonder what <hi>Englands</hi> Parliament is a doing; and all at home that love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt more than their own <hi>Intereſt</hi> and <hi>Notions,</hi> to be filled with unſpeakable trembling and aſtoniſhment, to wit, what God means to do with this poor bleeding Church, and State.</q>
               <q>If you mean that <hi>England</hi> ſhall be turned into a Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Commons,</hi> Aug 22. 1645 <hi>p. 29.</hi>
                  </note> and be over run with <hi>Atheiſm, and Hereſie, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phainneſs, and Blaſphemy,</hi> you may hold your hands, and you need not do it long.</q>
               <q>The Errours and Innovations under which we ſo<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Commons,</hi> Feb. 19. 1645. <hi>p. 25.</hi>
                  </note> much groan'd of latter years, were but <hi>tolerabiles ineptiae,</hi> tolerable trifles, Childrens play, compared with theſe damnable Doctrines, Doctrines of Devils, as the Apoſtle calls them: Polygamy, Arbitrary Divorce, Mortality of the Soul; No Miniſtery, no Churches, no Ordinances, no Scripture; yea, the very Divinity of Chriſt and the Holy Ghoſt queſtioned by ſome, deny'd by others; And the very Foundation of all theſe laid in ſuch a Schiſme of boundleſs Liberty of Conſcience, <hi>viz.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what you will, and Preach what you believe, and ſuch lawleſs ſeparation of Churches: and all theſe not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42597:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> not only whiſpered in Corners, but Preacht on the Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>top, yea, publiſht in <hi>Print</hi> before your faces with ſo much virulency and impudence, that I verily believe no Age ſince the Apoſtles time could ever parallel.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Commons,</hi> Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 26. 1649. <hi>p. 25.</hi>
                  </note>
               </q>
               <q>There be a Generation of men in the Land that ſtand up for all kind of falſe Worſhip; that every man may <hi>Worſhip God after his own Conſcience;</hi> or if they will not own it in words at length, they will have it in figures: And if they may not, are ready, not only to cry, but to act Perſecution<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>John L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ot Serm. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Commons,</hi> Aug. 26. 1645. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>p.</hi> 30. London, <hi>printed for Andr. Crook at the Green Dragon in</hi> Pauls <hi>Church yard. 1645.</hi>
                  </note> and that to purpoſe: for while they cry Perſecution <hi>gladio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oris,</hi> they are ready to act Perſecution <hi>ore gladii,</hi> I pray God it may never be Engliſh'd.</q>
               <q>There is a great talk of, and pleading for <hi>Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> for men do in matters of Religion, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did in the book of <hi>Judges,</hi> whatſoever ſeemeth good in their own eyes; and how that proved there, there are ſad ſtories that relate: I ſhall not go about to determine the queſtion, whether the Conſcience may be bound or not, though for mine own ſatisfaction, I am reſolved it may, and hold it a truer point in Divinity that <hi>Errans conſcientia liganda,</hi> than <hi>ligat,</hi> but certainly <hi>the Devil</hi> in the <hi>Conſcience</hi> may be, nay he muſt be bound, or elſe you act not according to<note place="margin">(a) Mr. <hi>Thomas Watſon before the Commons,</hi> Dec. 27. 1649. <hi>p. 17. London printed for Ra. Smith at the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e in Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil. 1649.</hi>
                  </note> that vigor that Chriſt hath put into your hands; nor according to that exactneſs that Chriſt requireth at your hands: it is true indeed which is ſo much talked of, that Chriſt alone muſt reign in the Conſcience, but it is as true alſo, that he doth ſo by the Power that he hath put into the hands of the Magiſtrate, as well as by his Word and Spirit.</q>
               <q>If Conſcience be a ſufficient plea, the Papiſt will come in for a Childs part. Conſcience muſt have a Rule, it binds only <hi>virtute praecepti,</hi> by vertue of a Precept. If
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42597:18"/> 
                  <hi>Conſcience</hi> againſt the Word. <hi>Deponenda eſt talis Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">M <hi>Hughes Sermon before the Commons,</hi> May 26. 1647. <hi>p. 34 Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don print for John Rothwell at the Sun and fountain in</hi> S. Pauls <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.</hi>
                  </note> Get conſcience better informed. I muſt ſay that the <hi>Toleration</hi> of all things muſt be a deſtructive princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to the State or Church where-ever it be allowed. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience hath ſhew'd us no leſs in Kingdoms and Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Called by Gods name. Theſe are only ſuggeſted which need a larger Treatiſe to ſtate fully. Ye Servants of Chriſt, take heed of yeelding to the pretences of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, the Devil and not Chriſt hath his Throne there; And no ſtronger hold for him than Conſcience, if he once take it Chriſt will not ſuffer him to ſhelter there; therefore ye may not, ſo much as in you lyeth.</q>
               <q>Do not other States, as ſome of the United Provinces<note place="margin">Doubt.</note> tolerate all theſe Hereſies, and protect them, and yet they proſper? who more? I deſire not to deal with other<note place="margin">Sol.</note> States, unleſs I might do them good, I am now only called to our own, yet others being made exemplary, a word in ſoberneſs and truth may not offend. I ſuggeſt only theſe thoughts.</q>
               <q>1. Can any man ſay, that proſperity is a ſign peculiar unto Truth? then let <hi>Rome</hi> come in and ſpeak more than any for outward proſperity.</q>
               <q>2. Are not ſpirituall wickedneſſes as odious to God as carnal; and are not theſe Hereſies ſuch, which God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns as works of the fleſh inconſiſtent with the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt?</q>
               <q>3. Hath God made an end yet of viſiting Nations for the ſins of them? When God hath done judging, were a better time to urge this Example than now. I pray God the evil day may not over-take thoſe States; the good Lord cauſe the Cup of trembling to paſs by them and purge their iniquities peacably. But I am preſſed in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42597:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> Spirit to ſay, God hath not ſpared ſuch State-Polities, which have ſought their own riſe by the ruine of God and his Truth. Witneſs <hi>Jeroboam</hi> the Son of <hi>Nebat</hi> who made Iſrael to ſin. And he bids ſin that doth not hinder it when he can—Gods Truth, my beloved, and not man example muſt be the Rule—if Hereſies yet muſt be, let us mourn for what we cannot help; it is a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable neceſſity when not allowed; it will be rejoycing in iniquity, either for State or Church wilfully to to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate.</q>
               <q>Though God hath given us glorious Victories over our<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Ed. Calamy, Serm. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the</hi> Lord <hi>May<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r, Jan. 14. 1645. p. 5.</hi>
                  </note> enemies, yet the Churches of Chriſt lye deſolate; Church-Reformation is obſtructed, Church-Diſcipline un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ed, Church-Diviſions increaſed. The famous City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> is become an <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> Separation from our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches is countenanced, <hi>Toleration</hi> is cried up, Authority aſleep.—It would ſeem a wonder if I ſhould reckon how many ſeparated <hi>Congregations,</hi> or rather Segregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">Serm. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lords, Dec. 25. 1644. p. 13.</note> there are in the <hi>City:</hi> What <hi>Churches</hi> againſt <hi>Churches,</hi> &amp;c. The Lord Knows that I mention theſe things with a ſad heart. Diviſions whether they be Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical or Political in <hi>Kingdoms, Cities,</hi> and <hi>Families,</hi> are infallible cauſes of Ruine to <hi>Kingdoms, Cities</hi> and<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſupra. p. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Families.</hi>
               </q>
               <q>Hereby the hearts of People are mightily diſtracted, many are hindred from Converſion, and even the Godly<note place="margin">p. 14.</note> themſelves have loſt much of the power of Godlineſs in their lives. I ſay the hearts of People mightily diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, while one Miniſter preacheth one thing as a Truth of the Goſpel, and another Miniſter preacheth the quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary with as much Confidence as the former.</q>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:42597:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <q>If Diviſions be ſo deſtructi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to <hi>Kingdoms, Cities and Families?</hi> this reproveth thoſe that are the Authors and Fomenters of theſe Diviſions that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re now amongſt us. Theſe are the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>endiaries of <hi>England.</hi> If he that ſets one houſe on fire deſerveth hanging, much more they that ſet a whole Kingdom on fire. If he that murders one man muſt be put to death, much more he that mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders three Kingdoms: Mark them, (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>Rom. 16. 17 That cauſe Diviſions and Offences contrary to the Doctrine which ye have learned, and avoid them,</hi> as the greateſt Enemies of <hi>England.</hi> Theſe are like the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mander that cannot live but in the fire of contention. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are of a Jeſuitical ſpirit. And no doubt the heads and hands of the Jeſuits are in all our Diviſions. Take heed of the Land deſtroying opinion of thoſe that plead for an illimited Toleration of all Religions, even of Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſme, Judaiſme, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Lord keep us from being poyſoned with ſuch an Errour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> * This Text riſeth up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt<note place="margin">Mat. 12. 25. <hi>Every Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf is brought to Deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </note> it. For it will divide a Kingdom againſt it ſelf. It will render it into a Thouſand pieces. It is a Doctrine di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary to your late Oath and Covenant. A Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that overthroweth al Church-Government, bringeth in Confuſion, and openeth a wide door unto all Irreligion and Atheiſm: For at the ſame door that all falſe Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons come in, the true Religion will quickly get out; and if it be as good for a man to live where nothing is lawful, as where all things are lawful, ſurely it is every way as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable to live where there are all Religions, as where there is no Religion at all.</q>
               <q>It is your Duty (Right Honourable) whom God hath betruſted with great power, to ſuppreſs theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:42597:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> and Differences in Religion by your Civil Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as far as your are able, leſt you be acceſſary un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. For God hath made you <hi>Cuſtodes utriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulae,</hi> Keepers not of the ſecond Table only (as ſome fondly imagine) but of the firſt Table alſo; and not only Keepers, but <hi>vindices utriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Tabulae,</hi> Puniſhers alſo of thoſe that tranſgreſs againſt either of them; for you are the Miniſters of God for good, and <hi>Revengers to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Wrath upon him that doth Evil,</hi> Rom. 13. 4. and God hath deputed you for the puniſhment of Evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 19. There be ſome that would blot out half your Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and reſtrain this good and evil, to civil good, and to evils only againſt men; But this is againſt that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rule, <hi>Non eſt diſtinguendum, ubi Lex non diſtinguit.</hi> Where the Law doth not diſtinguiſh, there muſt not we diſtinguiſh. Tell me I beſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch you, ſhall it be lawful for Magiſtrates to puniſh thoſe that deſtroy mens bodies, but not thoſe that deſtroy mens Souls? Shall they be blamed for ſuffering men to draw people away from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Laws of the Land, and to themſelves, and not alſo for ſuffering men to draw away people from the Truth of the Goſpel, and from the ways of God, ſuch as <hi>Hymenaeus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> who overthrew the Faith of ſome, and their Words eat as a Canker? Shall Chriſtian-Magiſtrates take up the Maxime of <hi>Tiberius, Deorum injurias Diis curae eſſe?</hi> Let God himſelf take care to vindicate himſelf from injuries committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God? as for me, I will (juſt like <hi>Gallio</hi>) take care of none of theſe things. Can Chriſtian Ears endure ſuch Language? Doth not God propheſie, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 49. 23. That in the New Teſtament, <hi>Kings ſhall be our Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:42597:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> Fathers, and Queens our nurſing Mothers? And how can a Chriſtian Magiſtrate diſcharge that duty a right if he hath not power from God, to puniſh thoſe that would poyſon the Souls of his weak Children with Hereſies and Soul deſtroying Opinions.</q>
               <q>Will you allow the Magiſtrate to Tyrannize over mens<note place="margin" type="runSum">Object.</note> Conſciences? By no means. But I believe it is the duty of Magiſtrates to keep men from infecting their Subjects<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> with Soul-deſtroying Errours. If thou haſt an Heretical Opinion, have it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o thy ſelf, and the Magiſtrate will not; nay, cannot meddle with thy Private Conſcience. But if thou laboureſt to infect others with thy Grace-deſtroying Opinions, I doubt not but the Magiſtrate is bound to keep thee from ſpreading thy Infection, to the undoing of the Souls of his Subjects; if he may lawfully ſhut up a man that hath the Plague upon his body that he may not infect others, why not the man t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hath the Plague of Hereſie upon his Soul, that ſo he may not deſtroy the Souls of Thouſands? Shall a Maſter in a Family have power to put away a Servant that is tainted with a groſs opinion, and yet not be called a Tyrant over that Servants Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? and ſhall not the chief Magiſtrate of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome have power to put out of his Kingdome (at leaſt to ſhut up from doing hurt) one that is his Subject and polluted with blaſphemous Heretical Idolatrical Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</q>
               <q>Is not the Kingdome the Magiſtrates Houſe and Family?</q>
               <q>This is a certain Rule, That all the ſins of the Kingdom<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sermon before the Com.</hi> Oct. 22. 1644. <hi>p. 26.</hi>
                  </note> which are committed by your connivence or allowance, are the Parliament ſins, and they call for a Parliament Repentance. And therefore I beſeech you ſearch and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:42597:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> try your hearts, and conſider how far you are acceſſary to the ſins of the Kingdom, that ſo you may be wrought up, not only to a perſonal, but a Parliament Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And if it doth appear, that you have, taken more care in ſetling your own Liberties, than in ſetling of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; if you have taken more care to build your own Houſes than Gods Houſe, this is is a crying Sin; and this makes you acceſſary to a Thouſand ſins that are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Kingdom. Again, if you do not labour ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your duty, and according to your power, to ſuppreſs the Errors and Hereſies, that are ſpread in the Kingdom; all theſe Errours are your Errours, and theſe Hereſies are your Hereſies, and they are your Sins, and God calls for a Parlimentary Repentance from you for them this day; You are the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and you are the <hi>Antinomians;</hi> and it is you that hold, <hi>That all Religions are to be tolerated,</hi> &amp;c. And theſe are your Errours if they ſpread by your <hi>Connivence.</hi> For, the ſins of the Sons of old <hi>Ely</hi> are imputed to old <hi>Ely</hi> himſelf. And when the People<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Rich. Baxters Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. Addition to Pref. Prop. 6. Lond. Pr. for Tho. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderhil at the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor and Bible in S.</hi> Pauls <hi>Church yard. 1659.</hi>
                  </note> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had prophained the Sabbath, <hi>Nehemiah</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with the Nobles of <hi>Judah</hi> for ſuffering them, and tells them, that it was they that did prophane it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſuffered the People to prophane it, <hi>Neh.</hi> 13. 17.</q>
               <q>It was none of the Old Cauſe that the People ſhould have <hi>Liberty,</hi> and the Magiſtrate ſhould have <hi>no Power in all</hi> matters of Gods Worſhip, Faith and Conſcience.</q>
               <q>And as it is not the Old Cauſe, ſo it is not a Good Cauſe.</q>
               <q>For firſt, it contradicteth the expreſs Revelation of the will of God, in the holy Scriptures. <hi>Moſes</hi> had to do in matters of Religion as a Magiſtrate; and ſo the ruling
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:42597:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> Elders of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that aſſiſted him; And ſo h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Jud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> as is well known, inſomuch that in <hi>Aſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> dayes, they Covenanted to put him to Death that would not ſeek the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> 2. It tendeth to the ruin of the Common-wealth: and therefore it is no good Cauſe. How God was provoked by <hi>Aarons</hi> Calfe, and by his Sons, that offered ſtrange fire which the Lord commanded not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 10. and what was the effect? and what benefit the Calves at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel</hi> brought to <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> and <hi>Jeroboam's</hi> houſe, and the High places, and others Errors about worſhip; brought to the Princes and People of <hi>Judah?</hi> we need not particularly recite.</q>
               <q>Law and Providence are quite changed, if Toleration of falſe Worſhip, and other abuſes of Religion, tend not to the ruine of the Common-wealth.</q>
               <q>If Magiſtrates muſt give Liberty for all to propagate a falſe Religion, then ſo muſt Parents and Maſters alſo: (for their Coercive power is rather leſs than the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates than more; and they are no more Lords of Faith or Conſcience;) But if all Parents and Maſters ſhould give ſuch a Liberty, it would be a crime ſo horrid in the nature and effects, as I am loath to name with its proper Titles.</q>
               <q>A <hi>pari:</hi> it tendeth to the Deſtruction of an Army, to give liberty to all men to do their worſt, to draw them to Mutinies and Rebellion; it tends to the ruine of Families that all have liberty to do their worſt, to tempt the Sons to Theſt and Drunkenneſs, and the Wife and Daughter to Whordome: it tends to the Deſtruction of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, if there be liberty for all to perſwade the People to Sedition and Rebellion: And therefore it muſt tend to the Deſtruction of the Church, and mans
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42597:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſouls, and conſequently of the Commonwealth in the chief reſpects<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if all have leave to do their worſt to preach up fidelity, Mahometaniſm, Popery, or any falſe Doctrine or Worſhip, againſt the great and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Truths.</q>
               <q>I leave it therefore to the judgement of all men that are not faſt aſleep in their ſecurity, and utterly unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the advantages of the Papiſts, whether this deſigne of engaging the Magiſtrate by a fundamental conſtitution, not to meddle with matters of faith and Worſhip, but leave them all to Chriſt alone, be not the preſent ſetting up of Popery in <hi>England</hi> and the delivering all the fruit of our labours, Prayers and Victories into the Papiſts hands.</q>
               <q>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But Liberty for Popery and Prelacy is ſtill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted.</q>
               <q>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> by whom?—But if there had been an excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt Popery put in, it would have been to little purpoſe, as long as a general Rule is laid down that condemned that exception. For if it be the ſtanding Rule, that matters of Religion and Faith, and all matters of Worſhip are out of the Magiſtrates power: to ſay then, <hi>that Popery ſhall be excepted from Liberty,</hi> is to ſay the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate ſhall intrude into the proper Office of Chriſt to reſtrain the Papiſts.</q>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Mr. Tho: Horton Ser: before the Houſe of Peers. Dec. 30. 1646. Loud. prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by F. Neile for Sam: Gelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand at the Brazen Serpent in Pauls Ch: yard. 1646. p. 35.</note>
               <q>Well, ſeeing theſe things are ſo; That ſin will find out <hi>us:</hi> let this be the uſe we make of it, to be carefull to find out <hi>it;</hi> and to begin with that firſt,</q>
               <q>This is that which lies upon us all; But eſpecially (to ſpeak a word in Seaſon) upon thoſe which have the Government of Kingdoms and Commonwealths com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto them, Theſe had need to find out ſin more
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:42597:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> eſpecially, for the ſafety and welfare of that State; which<note place="margin">P. 36.</note> they have the ordering and managing of.</q>
               <q>Firſt, their own Perſonal Sins.</q>
               <q>Secondly they are to find out alſo the ſins of the<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 37, &amp; 38.</note> 
                  <hi>Kingdom.</hi> I have already adminiſter'd ſome help in this performance, by the hint of thoſe Sins before mention'd; all which I humbly deſire may be taken into ſerious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and eſpecially (which grows ſo much upon us and which threatens ſo much evil to us) the Sin of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertiniſme</hi> and <hi>Toleration,</hi> which is the ring-leader of all the reſt, and involves all others with it. O that this ſhould ever be once mentioned amongſt us here in <hi>England,</hi> who have enjoyed ſo much of the Goſpel of Truth as we have done; derived to us from our Godly fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſealed to us by the blood of the Martyrs, proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted with ſo many bleſsings, and victories, and gracious ſucceſſes both of former and latter times to the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration both of Enemies and Friends; is this the fruit and iſſue of all that God hath done for us? and do all over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Reformation come to this? Surely God cannot but take it very ill from us, that we ſhould but incline and lean hereunto; As he ſaid to <hi>David</hi> of his building of the Temple; Thou didſt well that it was in thine heart, and accordingly was well pleaſed with him. So will he ſay to us, of our contrary carriage; That it is ill that it is in our heart; if ſo be, it be come ſo far, as I hope it is not. What? when we have ſo much appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt Popery<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Superſtition, ſhall we now begin to think of Indifferency and Toleration? Certainly it's but a ſorry exchange of a bad Religion for none. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though indeed it will be no exchange, but rather a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Confirmation: Toleration of all other Errours doth
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42597:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> but ſtrengthen Popery, amongſt the reſt; which will at leaſt think ſo well of it ſelf, as to come in for a Childs part.</q>
               <q>There is a Generation who look for much at your<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Lazar. Seaman Ser: before the Comm: Sep. 25. 1644. Lond. printed by E. G. for J. Rothwell at the, Sun in Pauls Ch: yard. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>4. p.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> hand, and yet ask nothing, I mean by way of humble Petition. When they find you, or themſelves in ſuch a poſture, as that they cannot be denied, it may be you may hear of them. Beſides the many looſe, prophane, and ſcandalous Miniſters, there are a new ſort riſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, who have thruſt themſelves into the Lords Vineyard. It's no leſs than Perſecution (ſo they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly give out) to deſire that their ſuſpitious Opinions may be examined according to the word of God, and they commanded to forbear the publiſhing and ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them for the preſent. There be many dangerous Books abroad, dangerous at leaſt, Ile ſay no more.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Liberty of Conſcience.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The bloody Tenent.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The compaſsionate Samaritan.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Baptiſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> Conſider alſo <note n="a" place="margin">Solomons.</note> his failings and beware of them. 1.<note place="margin">p. 44.</note> he had many Wives, even ſeven hundred Wives, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, and three hundred Concubines: <note n="b" place="margin">1 Kings 11. 3.</note> let not us have as many Religions. There's ſome Analogy between the one and the other. 2. There was in his dayes firſt a Connivance at Idolatry, then open Toleration, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Apoſtacy, theſe Wives turned away his heart after other Gods; <hi>v.</hi> 4. he built an high place for <hi>Chemoſh</hi> the Abomination of <hi>Moab,</hi> and for <hi>Molech</hi> the Abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:42597:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the Children of <hi>Amm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi> and likewiſe did he for all his ſtrange wives, <hi>v.</hi> 7, 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Obſerve the Gradation, firſt Connivence, then open Toleration, here withal Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy.</q>
               <q>No Reformation of Religion now: now nothing w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comen Ser<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> before the Parliament Sept. 12. 1644. Lond printed for Ch: Mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith, 1644. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note> ſatisfie ſome, but a <hi>Toleration of all Religion, and all Opinions;</hi> Church. Government, Diſcipline is to ſome a fiction, to others Tyranny, and Perſecution, An Brethren, this is a Provocation and will be a Provocation, for this God may turn us into the Wilderneſs again.</q>
               <q>We are grown beyond Arminianiſme, Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, Anabaptiſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we are come (I mean many among us) to down-right Libertiniſm. There are two Opinions, which if encourag'd (and they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courag'd if connived at) will open a door to Turciſme,<note place="margin">P. 36.</note> Judaiſme, Atheiſme, Polytheiſme, any monſter of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion. The one is, That every man is to be left to the Liberty of his own Religion, an opinion contended for by the bloody Tenets, John Baptiſt, Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, An opinion moſt pernicious and deſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uctive, as to the ſouls of men, ſo to the Common<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> weale of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</q>
               <q>
                  <hi>Libertas illa quidlibet credendi</hi> (ſaith Gerard) <hi>nihil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liud quam Libertas errandi, &amp;c.</hi> That L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>berty of believing what men will (or of holding what faith they pleaſe) is no other than a liberty of erring, and of erring in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that concerns the eternal Salvation of the Soule, wherein to erre, cannot but be moſt dangerous and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive—Diverſity of Religion diſ-joynts and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracts the minds of men, and is the Seminary of perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual hatreds, jealouſies, ſeditions, warres, if any thing in the world be; and in a little time, either a Schiſme in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:42597:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> the State begets a Schiſme in the Church, or a Schiſme in the Church begets a Schiſme in the State. That is, either Religion in the Church is prejudic'd by Civil Contentions, or Church controverſies and diſputes about Opinions break out into Civil Warres. <hi>Men will at laſt take up Swords and Spears, inſtead of Pens: and defend by Armes what they cannot do by arguments.</hi> Once for all, it is the Preſervation and Reformation of Religion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which you have Covenanted to endeavour, and not a Liberty of Opinion; that will conſiſt with neither. It is the Extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of Hereſie and Schiſme that you have Covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: which if to be connived at, why doth the Apoſtle reprove the Corinthians for their Schiſm, ſo much? and why doth our Lord Jeſus commend the Angel of the Church of Epheſus, for trying thoſe which ſaid they were Apoſtles, and were not? And why is the Angel of the Church of <hi>Thyatira</hi> reproved for ſuffering that woman <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabel,</hi> who called her ſelf a Propheteſs, to teach and ſeduce: if once we come to this, that any man be ſuffered to teach what he pleaſeth, to ſeduce whom he liſt, to be of what faith, or Religion ſeems good in his own eyes, farewell Covenant, farewell Reformed Religion, farewell the Peace and Glory of England, if that day once come. But you (Right Honourable) I hope better things of you though I thus ſpeak. I hope while you live and ſit in Parliament, this ſhall never be. It is not uſual, nay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is not poſſible that they which love God ſecretly, ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire<note place="margin">Serm.: at Pauls Feb. 8. 1646. Lond. printed for Ch: Mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith 1646 p. 14.</note> to cheriſh differing Religions; for it is moſt certain he that admits contrary Religions, believes neither of them.</q>
               <q>But then the queſtion will be, Seeing there will be difference of judgement and Opinion, while we are upon
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:42597:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> earth, then how, or how far is this difference of judgment<note place="margin">P. 14.</note> to be permitted? how or wherein may Chriſtians differ from one another in judgment, and yet ought to be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated and born with?</q>
               <q>This is my Brethren a very grave and difficult Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> and to me, conſidering how many places there are wherein the holy Ghoſt calls upon us to endeavour to be of one mind, of the ſame mind, and of the ſame judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; it is eaſier to tell you, wherein we may not differ in judgement, and wherein differences in judgement may not be <hi>tolerated,</hi> than to tell you wherein they may.</q>
               <q>Firſt therefore, I ſay, that as an abſolute unity in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that we ſhould all be of the ſame mind in all things, is ſcarce to be attained in this life, though it be to be endeavoured; ſo an Univerſal and abſolute Liberty of judgement, for every man to differ when he pleaſeth, and in what he pleaſeth, to be of what Opinion and faith he will, is not to be endeavoured if it might be attain'd, nor is it to be tolerated or permitted. I know no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, no pretence of warrant for it, in all the Book of God: Scripture no where ſaith, Let every man be of what opinion, and of what faith he pleaſeth, let every man be left to his own judgement.</q>
               <q>Particularly, Liberty of Opinion or judgement is not to be granted, or indulged, in ſuch things as are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to God, and deſtructive to the ſouls of men; nor wherein the Difference of judgement and opinion will neceſſarily and unavoidably, <hi>ex natura rei,</hi> produce a rent and Schiſme in the Church of Chriſt. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 10. Now I beſeech you Brethren, by the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeak the ſame thing, and that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:42597:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> there be no Diviſions among you: but that ye be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly joyned together in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgement. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 17. I beſeech you Brethren mark them that cauſe Diviſions and Offences among you, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Doctrine that you have receiv'd. And—what? Tolerate them? no, avoid them. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 12. I would they were even cut off that trouble you. Nothing can be clearer than theſe Scriptures are, againſt the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration of all Doctrines, and particularly of thoſe that trouble, rend, divide the Church.</q>
               <q>But (to ſpeak a little to the Poſitive) if there be a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and a Liberty of judgement left, it is firſt in ſuch things as are not clearly and poſitively laid down in Scripture, and therefore are not of the Fundamentals, and eſſentials of Faith and Worſhip; for there is for theſe, clear and undoubted Light in Scripture.</q>
               <q>Secondly, it is in things that are of private and ſingle practice, and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of open converſe, or Church fellowſhip and Communion. And yet even in theſe thing; this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty is not to be aſſumed, at leaſt, not to be practiſed without much tenderneſs and circumſpection<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </q>
               <q>Firſt, care muſt be had of keeping thoſe Opinions wherein we differ from others, private to our ſelves, not troubling or perplexing the Conſciences of others with them. This is the injunction: <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 22. Haſt thou Faith? have it to thy ſelf before God. The Faith there ſpoken of, is a particular perſwaſion, touching the free uſe of all creatures, and the Liberty of all dayes. And this Faith, this perſwaſion was according to the truth (as is clear by the Apoſtles Argumentation in that chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) yet ſaith the Apoſtle, Haſt thou Faith? have it to thy ſelf before God: do not ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I am fully perſwaded of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:42597:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> my liberty, and therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ought to profeſs it, and hold it out in my pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> whatever become of others; it is the truth of God, and I muſt hold it forth: No ſaith the Apoſtle, have it to thy ſelf. And if a man who hath a private opinion in <hi>re media,</hi> muſt keep it to himſelf, though it be a truth, much more muſt they whoſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions are falſe and erroneous. Certainly there is ſcarce any difference of judgement ſo ſmall, and in it ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable, but the divulging and propagating of it, may prove very dangerous and pernitious, and in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent intolerable.</q>
               <q>Suppoſe a man ſhould be of this Opinion, that it is unlawful to eat things ſtrangled, or blood: if ſuch a man keep his Opinion to himſelf, and make it a rule only to his own practice: let him enjoy it till he can be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe informed, and perſwaded in his Conſcience. But if he will now go publiſh this Opinion, and intangle the Conſciences of others; and ſeek to draw diſciples after him, and make a party, and cauſe diviſion and diſſention amongſt the People of God.</q>
               <q>This is not to be tolerated: Private perſons of a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering judgement, if they live quietly, frequent the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Aſſemblies of Worſhip, and are nor diſcerned to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the peace either of State or Church, by any ſecret underminings, are to be tolerated, in hope of their conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and for publick peace ſake. But if theſe men ſhall begin to ſpread their errors in publick, to inveigle and draw others to them, to beguile the ſimple, and ſo to trouble the publick peace, they are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained.</q>
               <q>Had all that profeſs the Goſpel in England, made Conſcience to be of the ſame mind, and the ſame judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:42597:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> with their Brethren, and the reſt of the Churches of Chriſt, as far as <hi>poſſibly;</hi> and where they cannot, where there is a neceſſity of differing, had they made Conſcience to keep their differences from appearing in Publick, to have their private opinions and faith to themſelves, and not intangle the weake with their doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Diſputations; forbearing to judge or deſpiſe thoſe that are not of their opinion, loving them ſtill as Brethren, not cenſuring them as profane, Antichriſtian, fighters againſt God, men that will willfully ſhut their eyes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Light; had theſe things (I ſay) been attented to, on all hands, our breaches had never been ſo great as now they are, non ſhould the lovers of truth and Peace have had ſo much cauſe to lament them,</q>
               <q>But where is the fault you will ſay? True it is there<note place="margin">P. 40.</note> are diviſions, ſad diviſions, danger threating diviſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>among us, but where is the fault? I know there are many that lay all the fault upon thoſe whom they call <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>esby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians, and ſay it is their rigour, and their pride and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, their Spirit of Domination that is the cauſe of all theſe diviſions; Thus ſay the <hi>Antinomians;</hi> and thus the <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> and thus the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and thus the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſay. Now the Lord judge between us and them, and let his people that hear judge this day.</q>
               <q>Who are they that divide in judgement from all the Reformed Churches of Chriſt in the world, that have Opinions and judgements differing from the Opinions &amp; judgements of all the Reformed Churches? we or the <hi>Anabaptiſts?</hi> we or the <hi>Separatiſts?</hi> we or the—? Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly they will all ſay, they are of the ſame Opinion with the Reformed Churches in fundamentalls as well as we: and their differences, are but <hi>in minutioribus.</hi> Now ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:42597:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> this to be true (as it may be in ſome of them why then d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>greſſe the Apoſtles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> why do they not if that it be in matters of leſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ment wherein they differ from us, why do not they keep their opinions private, and have their faith unto themſelves before God? why do they upon ſo ſmall differences (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the differences be ſo ſmall) withdraw from Communion with us and the reſt of the Churches, and gather themſelves into diſtinct and ſeparate Churches,—their holding one head &amp; one faith, doth not excuſe them from being guilty of breach of Unity and down <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight Schiſme, ſo long as the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hold not one body, one baptiſme <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">Beza ann t. in 1 Cor. 1. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp;c.</hi> Schiſme or diviſion (faith he) is this w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> men are ſo addicted to ſome men, or to ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward rites, that though they do agree in the chief points of Religion; yet they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> their minds, and engage themſelves into parties and factions: Now who are they, that though they profeſſe to agree with us in Doctrine have yet made a ſeceſſion, withdrawn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves gathered Churches, engaged Parties?</q>
               <q>Conſider and give ſentence.</q>
               <q>Who are they that have moſt broken the band of Love? There is great fear will at the Presbeterians will do if once they get power into their hands; but in the mean time what do others? who are they that brand their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren with the Title of, Proud Time-ſervers, Prelaticall, Tyrannicall, Antichriſtian? And what is this leſſe than Perſecution.</q>
               <q>Who are they that have been fartheſt from conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending to their Brethren for peace and union ſake? were it fit, I could ſay ſomething of this, yea much, I could tell you much hath been yielded and much more
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:42597:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> would be yielded, yea almoſt any thing, but that one thing that would lay a foundation of perpetual Diviſion and diſ-union on families. Church, Kingdom? Who are they that profeſs an utter impoſſibility of reconciliation or union, and plead for nothing but <hi>Toleration, Toleration,</hi> and ſome for <hi>Toleration</hi> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omoſt Latitude, to <hi>Papiſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Turks,</hi> the very artifide whereby the <hi>Arminians <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Holland</hi> ſought to gain a party, and ſtrength unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? Reſolve theſe Queſtions, and they will reſolve you who are moſt guilty of theſe Diviſions.</q>
               <q>By a Declaration ſet forth above Thirty years ago,<note place="margin">M. <hi>Richard. Vines Ser. before the Com: March 10. 1646. Lond. print. for Abel Roper. 1647 p. 1.</hi>
                  </note> King <hi>James</hi> (of famous memory was pleaſed to let the World know, not only how ill he reſented, and how much he deteſted the <hi>Vorſtian,</hi> and <hi>Arminian</hi> Doctrines, then newly born and in their ſwadling-cloaths; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo how ſollicitouſly he interpoſed with the States Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the United Provinces againſt their admittance of <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rſtius</hi> into the place of <hi>Divinity</hi> Profeſſor of <hi>Leiden,</hi> or into their Country<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And that he might decline the envy of being in <hi>aliena Republica curioſus,</hi> he beats him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon that common rule <hi>paries cunt proximus ardet,</hi> when a neighbours houſe is on fire, it concerns all in the Neighbourhood to look about them, this vigilancy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns our (I know not what to call it, I wiſh no worſe might be ſaid than) inſenſibleneſs and ſecurity. For what were thoſe ſparks at that time ſmoaking in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote corner, in compariſon of that fire which now flames forth at a very corner of our houſe, blown up by that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or liberty of all Religions, which may be juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called, the Golden Calf of theſe times, whereunto many are not unwilling to contribute their ſtrength &amp; Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, and whoſe Birth-day, they would not fear to call <hi>fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:42597:27"/> Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> acceptable day unto the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s which are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue amongſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, either by infecting perſons of place and Quality, grown into that boldneſs? or by carrying away, <hi>Bar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abas</hi> alſo crept into that cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit? or by ſpreading far and wide, riſen to that ſtrength? that they do fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, if not ſeem able to put into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ger of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing, our common faith, publick Worſhip, authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed Miniſtry, long and much expected, and promiſed Reformation. This to the common Enemy, is the Cape of good hope; the ſound part are afraid, leſt the Truth ſhould come to beg for poor quarter, and be led Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, following the Chario<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of triumph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Liberty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſome think that Epiſcopacy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in his Pont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ficalibus, may by this means be retrived, and recalled from exile, to which it was ſentenced by the Covenant, many that are as diſtant in their Opinions as the two Pol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, yet moving upon one axeltree, or tied together by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>s of common Intereſt, doubt not but by laying their ſtocks together, they ſhall be able to bid fair for a <hi>Toleration.</hi>
               </q>
               <q>And that we might no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be leſt alone to wonder at our ſelves, our ſympathyzing Brethren abroad do wonder alſo That we ſhould be made the common Sewreto receive the Garbage of other Churches; and that their ſtinking ſnuffs ſhould be allowed Candleſticks here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </q>
               <q>In this ſad poſture of things, all mens eyes have been upon the Parliament, and every one ſaith, Is there no Balm in <hi>Gilead?</hi> Is there no Phyſitian there? why then is not the health of the Daughter of my People recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</q>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eon Aſh Serm: before the Lords Feb. 26. 1644. Lond. print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Brewſter, 1645. p. 32.</hi>
               </note>
               <q>Endeavour vigorouſly to compound our Differences in Eccleſiaſtical concernments. Alas, alas, my heart
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:42597:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> akes, becauſe of our breaches. Let mine eyes run down with tears night and day, and let them not ceaſe, for the Virgin Daughter of my People is broken with a great breach, with a very grievous blow, <hi>Jer.</hi> 14. 17. What Factions, and Fractions, what Schiſmes and ſeparations, what Rents and Diviſions are in this poor, diſtracted di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Church of <hi>England?</hi> how ſhould either King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or Church divided ſtand? God forbid, but tender reſpect ſhould be had to tender Conſciences. But (Right Honourable) I beſeech you take heed, leſt under that pretext, you think of Tolerating all Religions amongſt us. Such Liberty (I am afraid) would uſher in Liberti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme,<note place="margin">P. 62.</note> and haſten our deſolation.</q>
               <q>It is commonly replied in Pulpits, in Preſſes, That<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>James Cranford Serm. before the L. Mayor Feb. 1. 1645. Lond. print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Char: Green. 1646. p. 11.</hi>
                  </note> a Toleration of all conſciences, even Antichriſtian, would be a ſoveraign remedy to cure all diſſentions, and an effectual means to compoſe the Wars of Chriſtendom: all the blood that hath for ſo many years been ſhed, is charged upon the reſtraint of this licentiouſneſs ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or malitiouſly termed Perſecution.</q>
               <q>I anſwer, it is beſides my purpoſe to diſcuſs this queſtion of Toleration, onely for the preſent I enquire Firſt; Would theſe men that ſo hotly deſend it grant that <hi>Toleration</hi> (if they had power in their hands) to others which they deſire for themſelves? I doubt it. The Arrians did ſometimes ſeem as earneſt enemies to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution as theſe men; yet when they had Authority on their ſide, they raiſed Perſecution againſt the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, more terrible than the heathen Emperours againſt the Chriſtians which the Churches of the Eaſt moſt<note place="margin">Binii Tom. 1. conc. p. 686.</note> grievouſly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> complained of.</q>
               <q>
                  <hi>Athanaſius</hi> at large deſcribeth, and having ſpoken
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:42597:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> much of their inhumane and more than b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty againſt all S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>s, all Ages<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> both living and dead con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Solicar.</note> that he had ſaid loſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> than their in humanity was<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe it exceeded all expreſſion.</q>
               <q>The Donatiſts did ordinarily plead for <hi>Toleration</hi> and ſeemed the moſt in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eterate enemies to all d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nce for Conſcience ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet when under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> they had g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en power, who can declare (ſaith <hi>Auſtin</hi>)<note place="margin">Con: lit Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til: l. 2. c. 82.</note> what h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vock they made of the Orthodox? All <hi>Africa</hi> was filled with blood and deſolation; men were rent ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons<note place="margin">Optat. cont. Parm. l. 2. 3.</note> dragged, infants ſlaughtered, women with child miſcarried, none were ſecure in their houſes, the wayes were not ſafe for travellers; the letters of them that boaſted to be the Captains of the Saints were ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible to all. Are our men led by another Spirit? Sure I am, that one of them, that with moſt earneſtneſs, or impudence pleads for <hi>Toleration,</hi> was lately of another mind in the caſe of Familiſts and <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>ians</hi> in <hi>Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>-England.</hi>
               </q>
               <q>Secondly, would ſuch <hi>Toleration</hi> conduce to the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing<note place="margin">P. 13.</note> of peace in the Common wealth? hath it ever done it? Poſſible it is, that the equality of Powers may perſwade each Party for a ſeaſon to ſuppreſs their inward rancour; can <hi>Toleration</hi> take it away, ſo that it ſhall not break out upon ſenſible advantages by the increaſe of ſtrength? let the experience of former Ages, and preſent times teach this.</q>
               <q>Errour may Tolerate Errour, <hi>ſavis inter ſe conven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>ſis;</hi> but can darkneſs agree with light? or <hi>VVolves</hi> with <hi>Sheep? Tertullian</hi> obſerves concerning <hi>Hereticks</hi> of old<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <note place="margin">De prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrip. cont. Haret. c. 41.</note> they agreed well enough one with another; for though they differed in private opinions, yet they joyned in one
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:42597:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> oppoſing of truth. You perſecute (ſaith <hi>Auſtin</hi> of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi>) where you are able; where you perſecute not, you are not able to doe it, reſtrained by the fear of Laws, or envie, or the multitude making reſiſtance.</q>
               <q>I have been long upon this point; but I will conclude it, with that ſolemn Embaſſie, which the Orthodox Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Aſſembled in Councell at <hi>Sirmium,</hi> ſent to the Emperour <hi>Conſtantius:</hi> I have inſiſted the longer, that<note place="margin">Athan. de Syn. Arim &amp; seleve.</note> it might appear to all, that the Toleration of Errour is not a way to Peace, as ſome men pretend, but to diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and confuſion: And yet I am not an enemy to Peace, but a friend to Truth, and Holineſs, without which, no Man ſhall ſee God.</q>
               <q>Miniſters ought now to be intent to the errours of the<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aſerious &amp; paſſionate Admonition to the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy; in the words of</hi> M. <hi>Tho: Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in his</hi> Gangraen: <hi>part: 1. p. 84 Lond. print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Ralph Smith at the Bible in Cornhill 1646.</hi>
                  </note> times, both in Doctrine and Practice, and obſerve what is the proper work of the day, and Preach accordingly; taking heed o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> being guilty of ſinfull ſilence, whileſt Chriſt and his Truth ſuffers. We have too many wounds with which we have been wounded, in the houſe of our friends: many Miniſters have and doe undoe us; ſome by their totall ſilence; others by ſpeaking too favourably, of the Sects, and too much daubing; 'tis high time now to ſpeak out, when the Truth of God, the Faith once delivered to the Saints, more pretious than our lives, is almoſt loſt, three Kingdomes almoſt ruin'd, and all the reformed Churches in their Truth and Peace, hazarded, they that can now be ſilent, well contented, and let the Wolves come freely and not barke, they deſerve to be accounted dumb dogs: Let therefore, all Godly Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Miniſters, who would not have all run to ruine, ſtir up themſelves and lift up their voices like Trumpets ſtand no longer looking on, as idle ſpectators, or halting
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:42597:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> between two; for he that is not now with God in his cauſe is againſt him, and he that gathereth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth—And that Miniſters in our times may be a means to prevent and ſuppreſs the Errours, <hi>Hereſies and Schiſmes,</hi> they muſt not onely often preach againſt them, but they ſhould ſet themſelves againſt all the wayes by which Errors are come in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and are farther coming in upon us, and oppoſe them by preaching and writing; as Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Preaching, the Gathering of <hi>Churches,</hi> and above all a <hi>Toleration,</hi> for that would be an open door, at which all kind of <hi>Hereſies</hi> would come in, and no man could keep them out: and therefore if Miniſters will witneſs for Truth and againſt Errors, they muſt ſet themſelves in a ſpecial manner againſt a <hi>Toleration,</hi> as the principal inlet to all <hi>Hereſie</hi> and Error; And if a <hi>Toleration</hi> be granted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all preaching will not keep them out: for as it hath been anſwered, the Patrons of Images (who plead let them ſtand, but Preach againſt the Worſhipping of them) that if they ſtand, Preaching will not take away all the danger; 'tis not ſufficient to keep the People from all Idolatry; ſo ſay I in this caſe. If a Toleration be granted, the Devil will be too hard for us, though we Preach never ſo much againſt them. A Toleration will undo all. Firſt bring in Sceptiſme in Doctrine, and looſeneſs of Life, and afterwards all Atheiſme.</q>
               <q>The Patrons of Error, becauſe they cannot at firſt plead for ſuch and ſuch Doctrines <hi>in terminis,</hi> and yet hold them, and would have them propagated, therefore they plead for a Toleration, which once being granted, they will come in then of courſe. O let the <hi>Miniſters</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore oppoſe Toleration, (as being that by which the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel would at once lay a foundation for his Kingdom to all
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:42597:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> Generations) witneſſe againſt it in all places, poſſeſſe the Magiſtrate of the evill of it, yea, and the People too, ſhewing them how if a Toleration were granted, they ſhould never have peace in their Families more, or ever after have command of Wives Children, Servants: but they and their Poſterities after them are like to live in diſcontent, and unquietneſſe of mind all their dayes.—I might ſhew how the Paſtors of the Reformed Churches (namely thoſe who were ſtars of the Firſt Magnitude)<note place="margin">p. 87.</note> were againſt the Toleration of Anabaptiſts, Libertines and other Sectaries in their time, and what they did and writ againſt it; <hi>Calvin, Zuinglius, Peter Martyr, Philip Melancthon, Zanchius, Beza, Knox, Bullinger, Muſculus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">p. 88.</note>—As alſo now in <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Queen Elizabeths days,</hi> learned Biſhops and Godly Miniſters were againſt the ſuffering of many Religions in this Kingdome: as Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> Biſhop <hi>Babington</hi> Biſhop <hi>Bilſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> &amp; Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> who in his learned workes on <hi>Revel:</hi> 2. 20. ſpeakes thus. Every man is not to be left to his own Conſcience; to teach and hold what Doctrine he will, But all ſuch men or women as teach erroneous Doctrine by the Government of the Church are to be reſtrained—Did I ſay <hi>the Arch Biſhops, Biſhops, Deanes Doctors,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">p. 89.</note> 
                  <hi>Court-Chaplains,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops-Chaplains,</hi> (for there were ſome of all theſe ſorts oppos'd) hazard the favour of Kings, Nobles, Great Courtiers the loſſe of all their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments, <hi>Arch-Biſhopricks, Biſhopricks, Deaneries,</hi> great liveings to wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hſtand a <hi>Toleration:</hi> And ſhall the Miniſters of our times ſuffer a <hi>Toleration</hi> of all Sects to come in upon us, in a time when the greateſt Reformation is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that ever was in this Kingdome, and a Parliament ſitting, and be either wholly ſilent or oppoſe fain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly; be
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:42597:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> afraid of diſpleaſing ſome great man, or hazarding lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle eſtate and liberty? was the Luke warm Angel whom God hath caſt out of his Church, for not being zealous enough, yet ſo zealous as to haz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd all againſt a <hi>Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Popery?</hi> And ſhall the <hi>Presbyterians O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thodox</hi> Godly Miniſters be ſo cold as to let <hi>Anabaptiſme, Browniſme, Antinomianiſme, Libertiniſme, Independency,</hi> come in upon us, and keep in a whole skin? Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Biſhops and their Chaplains ſhall riſe up in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the Miniſtry of this Generation, who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared againſt the mind of the King, Councill, and ſo powerful a faction as was for Popery, and the <hi>Toleration</hi> of it in thoſe dayes, if they be ſilent or meally mouthed, beſides the ſhame and diſhonour of it here, before the Churches abroad, and good men at home, who will lay all the blame upon the Miniſters, and ſay, We may thank them for this, for dealing no more freely, nor faithfully with the Kingdom, crying out an unworthy Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, an unworthy Miniſtry in City and Country, to ſit ſtill, and ſuffer all theſe Errors and poyſonous Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, in Books, Sermons, to come in upon us, and to paſs unqueſtioned.</q>
               <q>O for ſome <hi>Gabriel Powells, Downams, Abbots,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">O for a <hi>Burgeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> a <hi>Calamy,</hi> a <hi>Caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> a <hi>Baxter,</hi> an <hi>Edwards &amp;c. to write Preach, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> to write, preach, remonſtrate, proteſt againſt the Errors and wayes of theſe times. Tis want of courage and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out hath undone us; and tis onely boldneſs and freedome in ſpeaking, to declare particularly ſuch books come forth, ſuch Sermons preached, ſuch practices plaid, ſuch perſons preferred and ſuffered, ſuch partia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ty uſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in reference to the Sectaries, that muſt reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us; there's no way to put a ſtop to things, and ſave all from ruine, but preſent courage and Heroick reſolution,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:42597:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> and lets ſpeak out, and ſuffer no longer a company of giddy cunning ſelf-ſeeking Sectaries to betray the truth of God, and to abuſe and undo two Kingdoms—Lets therefore fill all Preſſes, cauſe all Pulpits to ring, and ſo poſſeſs Parliament, City, and the whole Kingdom againſt the Sects, and of the evil of Schiſme and Toleration, that we may no more hear of a Toleration, nor of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated Churches being hateful names in the Church of God. <hi>AMEN, AMEN.</hi>
               </q>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus far, theſe Famous Divines, whoſe very words I have tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and that faithfully; never adding ſo much as one ſyllable of my own, unleſs in the Margin, where I have ſometimes taken a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Liberty.</p>
                  <p>I do much hope (upon a ſerious peruſal) you will confeſs theſe <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies</hi> both pertinent and convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing; and therefore I might here
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:42597:31"/> take occaſion to conſult my own eaſe, and your patience, but becauſe (as I have found by ſad experience) <hi>prejudices</hi> are ſtrong, and evill <hi>habits</hi> (which have been long in contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting) are not ſuddenly removed, (as an effectual <hi>means</hi> (through Gods bleſſing) of your farther convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) I shall intreat your peruſal of theſe following <hi>Authorities.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="half_title">
               <pb facs="tcp:42597:31"/>
               <p>A LETTER OF THE Presbyterian Miniſters in the City OF LONDON <hi>Preſented the Firſt of</hi> Jan. 1645. <hi>to the Reverend Aſſembly of</hi> DIVINES, Sitting at Weſtminſter by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Parliament, AGAINST Toleration.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:42597:32"/>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:42597:32"/>
               <head>To our Reverend, Learned, and Religious Brethren, the Prolocutor, and the reſt of the Divines Aſſembled, and now ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> by Authority of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Theſe preſent.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reverend and beloved Brethren,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>WE are exceedingly apprehenſive of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirableneſs of our Churches Peace, and of the pleaſantneſs of Brethrens Unity, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that when Peace is ſet upon its proper Baſis, <hi>viz.</hi> Righteouſneſs and truth, it is one of the beſt Poſſeſſions, both delectable and profitable: like <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> ointment, and the dew of <hi>Hermon.</hi> It is true by reaſon of different lights, and differing ſights among Brethren there may be diſſenting in Opinions; yet, <note n="a" place="margin">What is the keeping conventicles or private meetings but ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from our Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
                  <hi>why ſhould there be any ſeparating from Church-Communion?</hi> The Churches Coat may be of diverſe colours, yet, why ſhould there be any rent in it? Have we not a Touchſtone of Truth, the good word of God; and when all things are examined by that word, then that which is beſt may be held faſt; but firſt they muſt be known, and then examined afterward. If our diſſenting Brethren after ſo many importunate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties would have been perſwaded (either in zeale to the truth, or in ſincere love to the Churches peace, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:42597:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> among Brethren<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or in reſpect to their own reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by fair and ingenious dealing, or <note n="b" place="margin">Yet the Miniſters of this perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion made as little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, Promiſes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ea, Oaths of Canonicall Obedience to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſans.</note> 
                  <hi>in conſcience to their promiſe made with the Miniſters of London now five years ſince,</hi> or any ſuch like reaſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble conſideration<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> at laſt to have given us a full narrative of their Opinions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Grounds of their Separation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wee are perſwaded they would not have ſtood at ſuch a diſtance from us as now they doe: But they choſe rather to walke by their own private ligts than to unboſome themſelves to us their moſt affectionate Brethren; and to ſet themſelves in an untroden way of their own, rather than to wait what our Covenanted Reformation, according to the word of God and <note n="c" place="margin">Shew us the example of one refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Church which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth her Miniſters liberty not to uſe her eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Rits and C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re-</note> 
                  <hi>examples of the beſt reformed Churches</hi> would bring forth: But the offence doth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> here<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is much that our Brethren ſhould ſeparate from the Church, but that they would endeavour <note n="d" place="margin">this is plainly our Brethrens deſigne and endeavour at this time.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et a warrant to Authorize their Separation from it, and to have Liberty (by drawing members out of it) to weaken and dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh it, till (ſo far as lies in them) they have brought it to nothing; this we think to be plainly unlawfull; yet this we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand is their preſent deſigne and endeavour.</hi> Wherefore (Reverend Brethren) haveing had ſuch large experience of your zeale of Gods glory, your care of his afflicted Church, your earneſt endeavours to promote the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Reformation of it, and of their ready concurrence with us in the improvement of any meanes that might be found conducible to this end; we are bold to hint unto you theſe our enſuing Reaſons againſt the Toleration of Independency in this Church.</p>
               <p n="1">1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Deſires and endeavours of Independents for a Toleration, are at this time extreamly unſeaſonable and preproperous: for,</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:42597:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>I. The Reformation of Religion is not yet perfected and ſetled amongſt us, according to our Covenant. And why may not the Reformation be raiſed up at laſt, to ſuch purity, and perfection, that truly tender Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces may receive abundant ſatisfaction, for ought that yet appears<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It is not yet known, what the Government of the Independents is, neither would they ever yet, vouchſafe to let the World know, what they hold in that point, though ſome of their Party, have been too forward to challenge the <hi>London Petitioners as led with blind Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and pinning their ſoules upon the Prieſts ſleeve,</hi> for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring an eſtabliſhment of the Government of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there was any Model of it extant.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We can hardly be perſwaded, that the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents themſelves (after all the ſtirs they have made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us) <note n="e" place="margin">The Pres<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>byterians (although often preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto) will not declare wherewith they would be all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, how far they mean to go, and where to stay in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> their deſires of Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention.</note> 
                  <hi>are as yet fully reſolved about their own way, wherewith they would be concluded,</hi> ſeeing they pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh not their modell (though they are nimble enough in publiſhing other things) and they profeſs Reſerves, and new Lights, for which they will (no doubt) expect the like Toleration, and ſo <hi>in infinitum,</hi> it were more ſeaſonable to move for Toleration, when once <hi>they are poſitively determined how far they mean to go, and where they mean to ſtay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. Their deſires and endeavours, are unſeaſonable, and unequal in divers regards.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Partly becauſe no ſuch Toleration, hath hitherto been eſtabliſhed, (ſo far as we know) in any Chriſtian State by the Civil Magiſtrate.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>It's noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery <hi>would not in the late times tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy.</note> 
                  <hi>Partly, becauſe ſome of them have ſolemnly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that they cannot ſuffer Presbytery; and anſwerable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:42597:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> is their practice in thoſe places where Independency pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. And partly becauſe <note n="g" place="margin">To grant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence unto a few, would offend many more of all Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> hy may not In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents, and all other Sectaries, deſire the ſame fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, in caſe they provide Readers or Churches.</note> 
                  <hi>to grant to them, and not to other Sectaries, who are free born as well as they, and have done as good ſervice as they to the Publick (as they uſe to plead) will be counted injuſtice and great Partiality;</hi> but to grant it unto all, will ſcarce be cleared from great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Independency is a Schiſme.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <note n="h" place="margin">Ye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready do, &amp; (in caſe your Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be granted) will draw our members from our Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; which ye acknowledge true Churches.</note> Independents do depart from our Churches, and ſo acknowledged by themſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They draw and ſeduce our Members from our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <note n="i" place="margin">Ye do in effect ſet up ſeparate Churches.</note> 
                  <hi>They erect ſeparate Congregations, under a ſeparate and undiſcovered Government.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Ye receive not the Sacraments (except ſome few) in our Churches, but at private meetings,</note> They refuſe Communion with our Churches in the Sacraments.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Their Miniſters refuſe to Preach among us as Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Their Members, if at any time they joyn with us in hearing the Word and Prayer, yet they do it not as with the Miniſterial Word and Prayer, nor as acts of Church-Communion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>No Schiſme is to be Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as ye grant. But Presbytery is a Shiſme</hi> Now, <hi>as much as Independency was by you declared to be</hi> Then. <hi>Therefore, (according to your own grounds) it is not to be Tolerated.</hi>
                  </note> Now we judge that no Schiſme is to be Tolerated in the Church <note n="*" place="margin">Schiſmes.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1. <hi>Cor. 1. 10. 1 Cor.</hi> 12. 25. <note n="*" place="margin">Diviſions.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 17. with 1 <hi>Cor. 3. 3. Gal.</hi> 5. 20.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. <note n="m" place="margin">The ſame would follow if Presbytery were Tolerated.</note> Many miſchiefs will inevitably follow upon
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:42597:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> this Toleration, and that both to Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
               <p>Firſt to the Church, as</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Cauſeleſs and unjuſt revolts from our Miniſtry and Congregations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Our Peoples minds will be troubled, and in danger to be ſubverted, as Acts</hi> 15. 24.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Bitter heart-burning among Brethren, will be fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, and perpetuated to Poſterity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The Godly, painfull, Orthodox Miniſtry, will be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged and deſpiſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>The life and power of Godlineſs will be eaten out by fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous diſputes, and vain janglings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>The whole courſe of Religion in private Families, will be interrupted and undermined.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Reciprocal Duties between perſons of neareſt and deareſt Relations will be extreamly violated.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>The whole work of Reformation, eſpecially in Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Government will be retarded, diſturbed, and in danger of being utterly fruſtrate and void, whileſt every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhall have liberty, upon every trivial diſcontent at Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterial Government and Churches, to revolt from us, and liſt themſelves in ſeparated Congregations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>All other Sects and Hereſies in the Kingdome will be encouraged to endeavour the like Toleration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>All other Sects and Hereſies in the Kingdome will ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard and ſhelter themſelves under the wings of Independency, and ſome of the Independents in their Books, have openly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowed, that they plead for Liberty of Conſcience as well for others, as for themſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>And the whole Church of England, in ſhort time will be ſwallowed up with deſtruction and confuſion. And God is
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:42597:35"/> not the Author of confuſion but of peace. 1. Cor.</hi> 14. 33.</p>
               <p>Secondly to the Commonwealth for.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>All theſe miſchiefs in the Church will have their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable influence upon the Commonwealth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The Kingdome will be wofully weakned by ſcandals and Diviſions; ſo that the enemies of it, both domeſtical and forreign, will be encouraged to plot and practiſe againſt it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>It is much to be doubted, leſt the power of the Magiſtrate, ſhould not only be weakned, but even utterly overthrown, conſidering the principles and practices of Independents toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their compliance with other Sectaries, ſufficiently</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">And are not Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples known to be ſo too.</note> 
                  <hi>known to be Anti-Magiſtratical.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">And as inconſiſtent with other Oaths im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by Lawful Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, which that was not</note> V: Such a Toleration is utterly repugnant and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with that ſolemne League and Covenant, for Reformation and defence of Religion, which not only both houſes of Parliament, but alſo perſons of all ſorts in both Kingdoms of England and Scotland, have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and with hands lifted up to the moſt high God have ſworn: <note n="a" place="margin">Which Oaths have been taken by moſt of the chief ſtricklers for Toleration, and with a true intention (it was hoped) to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the ſame.</note> which Covenant likewiſe, both you, and we, and thoſe that moſt earneſtly purſue the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of Toleration, have made (or ſhould have made) <hi>in the preſence of almighty God, the ſearcher of all hearts with a true intention to performe the ſame, as we ſhall anſwer at that great day, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be diſcloſed. for</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>This is oppoſite to the Reformation of Religion, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:42597:35"/> to the word of God, and the example of the beſt reformed Churches, Article</hi> 1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <note n="n" place="margin">The To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration of Presbytery is no leſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to the conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and uniformity of all the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes than Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency.</note> 
                  <hi>It is deſtructive to the three Kingdomes neareſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction and uniformity in Religion and Government, which might lead us and our Poſterity after us as Brethren to live in faith and Love Art.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <note n="o" place="margin">Seeing Presbytery is as much a Schiſme from Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy, as Epiſcopacy or Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency was from Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, why do they now, inſtead of extirpation, deſire the Toleration of it, contrary to your Covenant.</note> 
                  <hi>It is plainly contrary to that extirpation of Schiſme and whatſoever ſhall be found contrary to ſound Doctrine, and the power of Godlineſs, which we have ſworne ſincerely, really, and conſtantly to endeavour without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <note n="p" place="margin">Toleration of Schiſme rendreth Magiſtrates and Miniſters acceſſary to the Errours, Sins, and Deſtruction of ſeduced and deluded People.</note> 
                  <hi>Hereby we ſhall be involved in the guilt of other mens ſins, and thereby endangered to receive of their Plagues Art.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>It ſeems utterly impoſſible (if ſuch Toleration ſhould be granted) that the Lord ſhould be one, and his name one in the three Kingdomes, Art.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>This will palpably hinder the Reformation of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, inevitably divide one Kingdome from another, and unhappily make factions and parties among the People con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary to this League and Covenant; of which evill offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whoſoever ſhall be found guilty, are reputed in the Words of the Covenant</hi> 
                  <note n="q" place="margin">The Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of deformity, even in little Matters, ſometimes cauſeth factions and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties amongſt the People. Let us have a care we be not Incendiaries, or evil In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments for Sacrilegious ſpirits to work by, ill affected as well to Presbytery as Epiſcopacy.</note> 
                  <hi>Incendiaries, Malignants,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:42597:36"/> Malignants and evil Inſtruments, to be diſcovered, that they may be brought to publick trial, and receive condigne punishment. Art. 4. &amp;</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Theſe are ſome of the many Conſiderations, which make deep impreſſions upon our ſpirits, againſt that great <hi>Diana</hi> of Independents, and all the Sectaries ſo much cryed up by them in theſe diſtracted times, <hi>viz.</hi> A Toleration, a Toleration. And however, none ſhould have more rejoyced than our ſelves in the eſtabliſhment of a Brotherly, Peaceable, and Chriſtian accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: yet this being utterly rejected by them, we cannot diſſemble how upon the fore-mentioned grounds, we deteſt and abhor the much endeavoured Toleration. Our Bowels, our Bowels are ſtirred within us, and we could even drown our ſelves in Tears, when we call to mind, how long, and ſharp a travel this Kingdom hath been in for many years together, to bring forth that bleſſed fruit of a pure and perfect Reformation; and now at laſt after all our pangs, and dolours and expectations, this real and through Reformation, is in danger of being ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Birth by a lawleſs Toleration, that ſtrives to be brought forth before it.</p>
               <p>Wherefore (Reverend and Beloved brethren) we could not ſatisfy our ſelves, till we had made ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of our Thoughts unto you about this matter, not that we can harbour the leaſt jealouſy of your zeal, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, or induſtry in the oppoſing, and extirpating of ſuch a root of gall and bitterneſs, as Toleration is and will be, both in preſent and future Ages; but that we may what lyes in us, endeavour mutually to ſtrengthen one anothers reſolutions, againſt the preſent growing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:42597:36"/> and that our Conſciences, may not ſmite us another day for ſinful ſilence, or ſluggiſh deficiency in any point of Duty, tending to the glory of Chriſt, Honour of the Truth, Peace of the Church, Perfection of Reformation, Performance of our Covenant, and Benefit of preſent and ſucceeding Generations.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From Sion-Colledge</hi> Lond. <date>Decemb. 18. 1645.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Subſcribed by <hi>Us</hi> your affectionate Brethren, and fellow-labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers in the work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, to whom Truth and Peace is very precious.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="royal_judgement">
               <pb facs="tcp:42597:37"/>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:42597:37"/>
               <head>The Judgment of King <hi>JAMES</hi> and, His Privy-Council againſt Toleration, Tranſcribed verbatim out of Judg <hi>Crook's</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, Term. Mich. <hi>Anno 2. Jacobi,</hi> parag. 13. Part. 2. p. 37.</head>
               <p>MEmorandum, that by command from the King, All the Juſtices of England, with diverſe of the Nobility <hi>viz.</hi> The Lord <hi>Elleſmere</hi> Lord Chancellor, the Earl of <hi>Dorſet</hi> Lord Treaſurer, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>Cranbourne</hi> Principal Secretary, the Earl of <hi>Nottingham</hi> Lord Admiral, the Earls of <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland, Worceſter, Devon</hi> and <hi>Northampton,</hi> the Lords <hi>Zouch, Burghley</hi> and <hi>Knowles,</hi> the Chancellor of the <hi>Dutchy,</hi> the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>London, Popham</hi> Chief Juſtice, <hi>Bruce</hi> Maſter of the <hi>Rolls, Anderſon, Gawdy Walmeſly, Fenner, Kingſmill, Warberton, Savil, Daniel, Yelverton</hi> and <hi>Snigg,</hi> were aſſembled in the Star Chamber, where the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour, after a long Speech made by him concerning Juſtices of Peace, and his Exhortation to the Juſtices of Aſſize; and in diſcourſe concerning Papiſts and Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:42597:38"/> Declaring how they both were diſturbers of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that the King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and to have the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the Juſtices their Reſolution in three things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Whether the Deprivation of Puritan Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters by the High Commiſſioners, for refuſing to Conform themſelves to the Ceremonies appointed by the laſt Canons was Lawful? Whereto all the Juſtices anſwered.</p>
               <p>That they had conferred thereof before, and held it to be lawful, Becauſe the King hath the Supream Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Power, which he hath Delegated to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, whereby they had the power of Deprivation, by the Canon Law of the Realm, and the Statute of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> which appoint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Commiſſioners to be made by the Queen, doth not confer any new power, but explain and declare the ancient power. And therefore they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eld <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> clear, That the King without Parliament might make Orders and Conſtitutions for the Government of the Clergy, and might deprive them, if they obey'd not. And ſo the Commiſſioners might deprive them. But they could not make any conſtitutions without the King, and the divulging of ſuch Ordinances by Proclamation is a moſt gratious Admonition; And for as much as they have refuſed to obey, they are lawfully deprived by the Commiſſioners <hi>ex Offici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> without Libel <hi>Et ore tenus convocati.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Whether a Prohibition be grantable againſt the Commiſſioners upon the Statute of 2 <hi>H. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> if they do not deliver the Copy of the Libel to the Party, whereto they all Anſwered, That that Statute is intended where the Eccleſiaſtical Judge proceeds, <hi>Ex officio &amp; ore tenus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:42597:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Thirdly, Whether it were an offence puniſhable, and what puniſhment they deſerved who framed Petitions, and collected a multitude of hands thereto, to prefer the King in a publick cauſe as the <hi>Puritans</hi> had done; with an Intimation to the King, That if he denyed their Suit many Thouſands of the Subjects would be diſcontented? Whereto all the Juſtices anſwered, that it was an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence finable at Diſcretion; and very near to Treaſon and Felony in the Puniſhment; for they tended to the raiſing of Sedition, Rebellion and Diſcontent among the People: To which Reſolution all the Lords agreed and then many of the Lords declared:</p>
               <p>That ſome of the <hi>Puritans</hi> had raiſed a falſe Rumour of the King, how he intended to grant a <hi>Toleration</hi> to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts: which Offence the Juſtices conceived to be hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly finable by the Rules of the Common Law, either in the Kings Bench, or by the King and his Council: or now ſince the Statute of 3 <hi>H.</hi> 7. in the Star-Chamber. And the Lords ſeverally declared how the King was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented with the ſaid falſe Rumour; and had made but the day before a Proteſtation unto them, That He never intended it, and that he would ſpend the laſt drop of Blood in his body before he would do it; and prayed that before any of his Iſſue ſhould maintain any other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion than what he truly profeſſed and maintained, that God would take them out of the World.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="actions_in_Parliament">
               <pb facs="tcp:42597:39"/>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:42597:39"/>
               <head>VOTES, &amp;c. Of the Honourable Houſe of Commons, <hi>Feb. 5. &amp;c.</hi> 1662. Upon Reading His Majeſties Gracious <hi>Declaration and Speech; &amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <date>Die Mercurii 25. Feb. 15. Car. R.</date>
               </opener>
               <p>Reſolved &amp;c. <hi>Nemine contradicente,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the humble Thanks of this Houſe, be returned to his Majeſty, for his Reſolution to maintain the Act of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Reſolved &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That it be preſented to the Kings Majeſtie, as the Humble Advice of the Houſe, That no Indulgence be granted to the Diſſenters from the Act of Uniformity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſt Gracious Sovereign!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THe Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes of the Commons houſe of Parliament did with great joy receive your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:42597:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> moſt Gratious Speech a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the opening this Seſſion of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>by in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ted to conſider of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Declaration of the Twenty ſixth of December laſt; they have with all Sobriety, Duty and Affection examind the Grounds thereof, and do by me preſent unto your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty their moſt hearty Thanks for the ſame, and humble Advice thereupon; both which I do beſeech your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, that you will vouchſafe me to deliver in their own words.</p>
               <p>May it pleaſe your most Excellent Majeſty.</p>
               <p>We your Majeſties moſt Dutiful and Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, the Knights, Citizens and Burgoſſes of the Houſe of Commons in Parliament Aſſembled, having with all fidelity and obedience conſidered of the ſeveral matters compriſed in your Majeſties late Gracious Declaration of the 26. of <hi>Decemb<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> laſt, and your moſt gratious Speech at the beginning of this preſent Seſſion.</p>
               <p>Do in the firſt place for our ſelves and in the names of all the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> render to your Sacred Majeſty the Tribute of our moſt hearty Thanks for that infinite grace and goodneſs, wherewith your Majeſty hath been pleaſed to publiſh your Royal Intentions of adhering to your Act of Indempnity and Oblivion, by a conſtant and Religious Obſervance of it. And our hearts are further enlarged in theſe returns of Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings when we conſider your Majeſties moſt Princely and Heroick Profeſſions of relying upon the Affections of your people, and abhorring all ſort of Military and Arbitrary Rule. But above all we can never enough remember, to the honour of your Majeſties Piety, and our unſpeakable Comfort, thoſe ſolemn and moſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearing Invitations of us your Majeſties Subjects to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:42597:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> Laws to be preſented to your Majeſty againſt the Growth and Encreaſe of Popery; and withall to provide more Laws againſt Licentiouſneſs and Impiety; at the ſame time declaring your own Reſolutions for maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Act of Uniformity.</p>
               <p>And it becomes us always to acknowledg and admire your Majeſties Wiſdom in this your Declaration, whereby your Majeſty is pleaſed to reſolve not only by Sumptuary Laws, but by your own Royal Example of Frugality, to reſtrain that Exceſs in Mens Expences w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is grown ſo General and ſo Exorbitant; and to direct our Endeavours to find out fit and proper Laws for Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of Trade and Commerce.</p>
               <p>After all this we moſt humbly beſeech your Majeſty to believe, That it is with extream unwillingneſs and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctancy of heart that we are brought to differ from any thing which your Majeſty hath thought fit to propoſe; And though we do no way doubt but that the unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Diſtempers of mens ſpirits, and the many Mutinies and Conſpiracies which were carried on during the late intervals of Parliament, did reaſonably incli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to endeavour by your Declaration, to give ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay to thoſe ill humours; till the Parliament aſſembled; and the hopes of indulgence, if the Parliament ſhould conſent to it, eſpecially ſeeing the prete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ers to this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence did ſeem to make ſome titles to it by virtue of your Majeſties Declaration from <hi>Breda.</hi> Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we your Majeſties moſt Dutiful and Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, who are now returned to ſerve in Parliament, from thoſe ſeveral parts and places of your Kingdom for which we are choſen, Do humbly offer to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties great Wiſdom, That it is in no ſort adviſable,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:42597:41"/> that there be any indulgence to ſuch perſons, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to diſſent from the Act of Uniformity and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion eſtabliſhed.</p>
               <p>For theſe Reaſons,</p>
               <p>We have conſidered the nature of your Majeſties Declaration from <hi>Breda,</hi> and are humbly of Opinion, That your Majeſty ought not to be preſſed with it any further.</p>
               <p>Becauſe it is not a promiſe in it ſelf, but only a Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Declaration of your Majeſties Intentions to do what in you lay, and what a Parliament ſhould adviſe your Majeſty to do; and no ſuch Advice was ever gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or thought fit to be offered; nor could it be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe underſtood, becauſe there were Laws of Uniformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty then in being, which could not be diſpenſed with but by Act of Parliament.</p>
               <p>They who do pretend a right to that ſuppoſed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, put the Right into the hands of their Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives whom they choſe to ſerve for them in this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who have paſſed, and your Majeſty conſented to the Act of Uniformity. If any ſhall preſume to ſay that a right to the benefit of this Declaration doth ſtill remain after this Act paſſed.</p>
               <p>It tends to diſſolve the very Bonds of Government, and to ſuppoſe a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſability in your Majeſty and the Houſes of Parliament to make a Law contrary to any part of your Majeſties Declaration, though both Houſes ſhould adviſe your Majeſty to it.</p>
               <p>We have alſo conſidered the nature of the Indulgence propoſed, with reference to thoſe conſequences which muſt neceſſarily attend it.</p>
               <p>It will eſtabliſh Schiſm by a Law, and make the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:42597:41"/> whole Government of the Church precarious, and the Cenſures of it of no Moment or Conſideration at all.</p>
               <p>It will no way become the Gravity or Wiſdom of a Parliament, to paſs a Law at one Seſſion for Uniformity, and at the next Seſſion (the Reaſons of Uniformity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing ſtill the ſame) to paſs another Law to fruſtrate or weaken the execution of it.</p>
               <p>It will expoſe your Majeſty to the reſtleſs importu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of every Sect or Opinion, and of every ſingle Perſon alſo, who ſhall preſume to diſſent from the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It will be a cauſe of increaſing Sects and Sectaries, whoſe numbers will weaken the true Proteſtant Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo far that it will at leaſt be difficult for it to defend it ſelf againſt them: And which is yet further Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thoſe Numbers which by being troubleſom to the Government, find they can arrive to an Indulgence, will as their Numbers increaſe, be yet more troubleſom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ſo at length they may arrive to a general Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which your Majeſty hath declared againſt, and in time ſome prevalent Sect will at laſt contend for an eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment, which for ought can be foreſeen, may end in Popery.</p>
               <p>It is a thing altogether without precedent, and will take away all means of convicting Recuſants, and be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the method and proceedings of the Laws of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly it is humbly concieved that the Indulgence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd will be ſo far from tending to the peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that it is rather likely to occaſion great diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance. And on the contrary; That the aſſerting of the Laws, and the Religion eſtabliſh'd, according to the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:42597:42"/> Act of Uniformity, is the moſt probable means to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a ſettled Peace and obedience throughout your Kingdom: Becauſe the variety of Profeſſions in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, when openly divulged, doth directly diſtinguiſh men into parties, and withall gives them opportunity to count their numbers; which conſidering the animoſities that out of a Religious Pride will be kept on foot by the ſeveral factions, doth tend directly and inevitably to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen diſturbance.</p>
               <p>Nor can your Majeſty have any Security that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or Worſhip of the ſeveral Faction, which are all governed by a ſeveral Rule, ſhall be conſiſtent with the Peace of your Kingdom.</p>
               <p>And if any perſons ſhall preſume to diſturb the peace of the Kingdom; We do in all humility declare, That we will for ever and in all occaſions be ready with our utmoſt endeavour and Aſſiſtance, to adhere to and ſerve Your Majeſty according to our bounden Duty and Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:42597:42"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Brethren!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have now given you my Authorities, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The private Teſtimonies of twenty emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Divines.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The publick Teſtimony of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Miniſters in the City of <hi>London</hi> (Sydoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally) met at Sion College.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Authority of that Wiſe and Learned King <hi>James</hi> and his Privy Council.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Votes and Reaſons of the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Commons Aſſembled in this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            <p>All which I have deſignedly rank'd in this method, that obſerving the <hi>order</hi> of <hi>nature,</hi> and beginning <hi>ab imperfectiori,</hi> I might gradually a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to that which is more <hi>perfect;</hi> for ſuch I think the Reaſons of the <hi>Houſe</hi> will be found; (to him that dare attempt them) (<hi>i. e.</hi>) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable and unanſwerable.</p>
            <p>I know not how it fares with other men, (I am no judg of their <hi>honeſty</hi> or <hi>Knowledg</hi>) but I am ſure, as to me the premiſes have appear'd ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:42597:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> I ſhould think the world might ſuſpect either <hi>my Intellectuals</hi> of <hi>Morals</hi> were I no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> apprehenſive of ſo convincing a Light.</p>
            <p>My Brethren, (that I may deal freely with you) I am perfectly amazed, and (I had almoſt ſaid) <hi>ſcandaliz'd,</hi> that <hi>men</hi> ſo eminent for <hi>learning,</hi> ſo noted for <hi>piety,</hi> and (if we may believe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves it being one of their grand Topicks for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence) ſo conſiderable for <hi>Policy,</hi> I ſay that theſe <hi>men</hi> ſhould ſo warmly concern <hi>themſelves</hi> for this <hi>Thing</hi> call'd <hi>Toleration,</hi> which (as I hope the premiſes have evinc'd) is not only <hi>deſtructive</hi> both to Church and State, but alſo (which pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent men would a little conſider) ſo directly <hi>contrary</hi> to their former <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Practiſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am very unwilling to make any unpleaſing Reflections, but 'tis the Language of the world (and I am not yet inſtructed to confute it) that it is not a <hi>Toleration</hi> (however pretended, as the moſt advantageous method that can at <hi>preſent</hi> be imploy'd) but a Reformation, that is, (as ſad experience hath explained it) a total <hi>Extirpation</hi> of whatever is contrary to their humours and deſigns) that each different <hi>Party</hi> endeavours to eſtabliſh.</p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:42597:43"/>
            <p>Now that this may not be rejected as a ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>deſign,</hi> only to make you odious to <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> (as is commonly objected) there are ſeveral Reaſons (at leaſt ſtrong conjectures) that ſeem highly to enforce the forementioned <hi>charge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am willing to conclude; and ſhall <hi>therefore</hi> give you my notions in <hi>groſs,</hi> leaving the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſis to your acuter Judgments.</p>
            <p>There are you know ſuch things in the world as a <hi>jus divinum</hi> of ſome one Form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a Solemn League and Covenant; both which as being directly contrary to your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Toleration,</hi> (had I but the leiſure or abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to improve them) might eaſily be reſolved into a Volumn of Arguments.</p>
            <p>But leaving this performance (if occaſion ſhall require) to the management of ſome abler Pen, permit me very calmly to beg your <hi>Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution</hi> to this following Propoſal.</p>
            <p>Were <hi>you</hi> in the ſame Condition, (<hi>i. e.</hi>) di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>you</hi> enjoy the ſame encouraging Circumſtance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that your Adverſaries, the true Sons of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church of <hi>England</hi> (through Gods great mercy and the Indulgence of a gracious Prince) are at preſent favoured with; <hi>then</hi> lay your hands upon
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:42597:44"/> your breaſt, and re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, as in the Preſence of the great God that ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udg the world; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would you then indulge either perſon or Parties that ſhould diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> from your) eſtabliſht Diſcipline, be it Presbyter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an or Independent, or any other whatſoever (<hi>e. g.</hi>) Whether would you then permit <hi>that</hi> Miniſter to preach publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that ſhould <hi>read the Service of our Church, wear a Surpliſe, uſe the Croſs in Baptiſm, Kneel at the Sacrament,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and not</hi> only ſo, but the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of whoſe endeavors ſhould be employ'd in perſuading others to the like practiſes, telling them that the contrary (by) you obſerved) was irreverent and indecent, &amp; therefore of all good Chriſtians to be loath'd and abhor'd, I ſay, tell me plainly;) Is it fit to grant a <hi>Toleration</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence</hi> to ſuch a perſon or no? if not, then (even your ſelves being judges) neither is it fit to <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate you,</hi> ſince <hi>your</hi> Principles and Practiſes are as diſtant from <hi>his</hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the true Son's of the Church of <hi>England</hi>) as his from <hi>yours,</hi> as deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to his, as his to yours and <hi>it is unreaſonable</hi> (ſays the defender of the <hi>London</hi> Miniſters Let. to the Aſſem.) <hi>that Independents ſhould deſire that toleration from Presbyters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they would not give</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anti-To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler.</hi> p. 16.</note>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:42597:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>to Presbyters;</hi> ſo ſay I, tis unreaſonable that <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents, Presbyters,</hi> or any other Sect ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that <hi>Toleration</hi> from <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> which they would not grant to <hi>Epiſcopacy. For with what face can I deſire a courteſie from him, to whom I do openly profeſs, I would deny the ſame Courteſie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now if you take the other member of the <hi>Contradiction,</hi> and ſay, <hi>you would tolerate the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd perſon,</hi> ſuppoſing him otherwiſe of a quiet and peaceable temper; let me then deſire you further to reſolve me, <hi>Are you perſuaded that the Church of England requires any thing ſinful as their condition of her Communion or not?</hi> if you ſay <hi>ſhe does not</hi> (I am no little troubled to mention it, but theres no evaſion) I muſt plainly tell you, you are no better then downright Schiſmaticks; for Schiſm in the proper notion of it, is nothing <hi>elſe</hi> but a <hi>cauſleſs Separation from that part of the viſible Church of which we were members:</hi> now there is no <hi>ſufficient cauſe</hi> for ſuch <hi>ſeparation</hi> but Sin, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vnleſs there be ſomething which is ſinful required as the Condition of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, it appears to me to be Schiſm to withdraw our ſelves.</hi> Def. of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ. p. 91.</note> it being the judgment of our beſt Writers upon that Controverſie, that nothing elſe could warrant our Separation from <hi>Rome</hi> but this, that ſhe required as conditions of her communion, ſomewhat <hi>in fide</hi> erroneous, or <hi>in facto</hi> impious.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:42597:45"/>
            <p>But if you are perſuaded (and ſome of you have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> at) <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe does require ſomething which is ſinful as the condition of her Communion,</hi> then the caſe is clear; the mask f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lls of; and I have finiſhed my task; for, for, ſince all ſin is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly the object, not only of our hatred and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ſation,</hi> but alſo of totall extirpation (it being every ones duty not only to avoid ſin himſelf, but (by all lawful ways and method<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der its commiſſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> others) I ſhall humbly leave it to his moſt Sacred M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>jeſty, and the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Parliament to conſider;</p>
            <p>Whether it be either Religion or Policy, to tolerate thoſe Perſons, or Parties, which are perſuaded in their Conſciences, that it is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary incumbent Duty, not onely to hate and deteſt, but alſo (by all thoſe ways and methods which they themſelves ſhall think lawful) to weaken, alter and extirpate the ſettled Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church? the which Alteration, what influence it may have upon the <hi>State,</hi> and how Deſtructive it may prove to His Majeſties Crown and Kingdoms, (I hope it is no breach of the <hi>Act of Oblivion</hi> to tell you) the experience of late years hath ſuggeſted a very fatal conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:42597:45"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <head>The Preface.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Author no ſcoffer at Religion</hi> page. 2.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Occaſion of this work.</hi> 5.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Author diſſatisfied about Toleration</hi> 7.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Toleration is unpracticable</hi> 8.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Petitioners for Tol. ſcarce intelligible in their Propoſals</hi> 9.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Teſtimonies of twenty eminent Divines againſt Toleration</hi> 11.
<list>
                     <head>Particularly,</head>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Aſh.</hi> 50.</item>
                     <item>Dr. <hi>Corn. Burgeſſe.</hi> 15.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi> 37.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Calamy.</hi> 33.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Caſe</hi> 28.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Cranford</hi> 51.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> 53.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Good</hi> 23.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Hardwicke</hi> 26.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Horton</hi> 39.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Hughes.</hi> 32.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Lightfoot.</hi> 31.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Newcomen.</hi> 42.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Reyner</hi> 28.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Salwey.</hi> 27.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Seaman.</hi> 41.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Thorowgood</hi> 24.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Vines</hi> 49.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Ward</hi> 19.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Watſon</hi> 31.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Letter of the Presbyterian Miniſters in the City of</hi> London <hi>to the Aſſembly, against Toleration</hi> 61.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:42597:46"/>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA</head>
            <p>PAge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2. line 20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> after theſe words <hi>Liberty of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> p. 46. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>this is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Tolerated,</hi> and place them in the fore-going line. There <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſmaller Errata's, which the Reader (as he pleaſeth) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> pardon.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42597:46"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
